<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Eliah's abatement: or, Corruption in the saints. Discovered and distinguished in a sermon, preached at Chatham in Kent, at the Funeral of that faithful minister of the Gospel, Mr. Gaulter Roswell, M.a. late preacher there. / By Tho. Case, M.A. and rector of Giles in the Fields.</title>
            <author>Case, Thomas, 1598-1682.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 176 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 83 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81240</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C828</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1882_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209895</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868746</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868746</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170519</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81240)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170519)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 234:E1882[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Eliah's abatement: or, Corruption in the saints. Discovered and distinguished in a sermon, preached at Chatham in Kent, at the Funeral of that faithful minister of the Gospel, Mr. Gaulter Roswell, M.a. late preacher there. / By Tho. Case, M.A. and rector of Giles in the Fields.</title>
                  <author>Case, Thomas, 1598-1682.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32], 135, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E.T. for Luke Fawn, and are to be sold at his shop at the sign of the Parrat in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octob:".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rosewell, Walter --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  James V, 17 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170519:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>ELIAH'S</hi> ABATEMENT: Or, CORRUPTION IN THE <hi>SAINTS.</hi> Diſcovered and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed in a Sermon, Preached at <hi>Chatham</hi> in KENT, At the Funeral of that Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Miniſter of the Goſpel, Mr. GUALTER ROSWELL, M. A. Late Preacher there. By THO. CASE, M. A. and Rector of Giles in the Fields.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>E. T.</hi> for <hi>Luke Fawn,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the ſign of the <hi>Parrat</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1658.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:170519:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170519:2"/>
            <head>To his much honoured FRIENDS,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>CHARLES BOWLS Eſq. High Sheriff of</hi> Kent;</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>PETER PETT Eſq. one of the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners of the Navie;</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>RICH. ISACKSON Eſq.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Capt. PHINEAS PETT,</hi> His Loving and Reſpected <hi>NEPHEW;</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Capt. JOHN PILGRIM, With the reſt of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of</hi> Chatham <hi>in</hi> Kent.</item>
               </list>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy and well-beloved Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE <hi>death</hi> of a faithfull Miniſter the Goſpel is no <hi>ſmall
<pb facs="tcp:170519:3"/>loſſe</hi> unto a people, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially when the <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of errour</hi> and <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction</hi> is gone out into the world: It is like the taking off a <hi>Shepherd</hi> from his <hi>Flock,</hi> when the <hi>Wolves</hi> are abroad; or, the <hi>Hen</hi> from her <hi>Chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens,</hi> when the <hi>birds of prey</hi> are upon the wing: It is like the removing of a <hi>Watch-man</hi> from his <hi>Watch-Tower,</hi> when the enemy is upon his march; a skilful <hi>Pilot</hi> from the <hi>Helm,</hi> or, the <hi>Helm</hi> from the <hi>Ship,</hi> in the midſt of a <hi>tempeſtuous</hi> and a <hi>flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuating
<pb facs="tcp:170519:3"/>Sea;</hi> like the ſlaughter of a <hi>General</hi> in the head of his <hi>Army,</hi> when the <hi>Enemy</hi> is ready to <hi>Charge.</hi> Surely none of theſe are of more fatal influence in the affairs of the <hi>worldly</hi> ſtate, then <hi>the other</hi> of the <hi>Evangelical.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſuch a juncture of time hath <hi>God taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from your head</hi> that Precious and Worthy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of His, <hi>your late Reverend and Faithful Paſtor,</hi> Mr. <hi>GUALTER ROSWELL;</hi> whoſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent <hi>abilities,</hi> unwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried labours, in <hi>publick,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:170519:4"/>and in <hi>private;</hi> impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial <hi>fidelity,</hi> and <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate ſpirit</hi> over pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing ſinners; and, in a word, his great <hi>inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity</hi> in all his miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial out-goings before you; I humbly conceive there are none among you but will thankfully acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, unleſs ſuch (poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly) whom either <hi>erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous principles,</hi> or <hi>looſe practiſes,</hi> occaſioned to look upon him, <hi>as their
<note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 4.16. <hi>An expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctas ut Quintilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur?</hi>
                  </note> Enemy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That this Lot may not be of ſo fatal conſequence unto you, accept I beſeech
<pb facs="tcp:170519:4"/>you a few <hi>Advices</hi> from him that loveth you.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ad∣vice. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>Be deeply ſenſible of your Loſs.</hi> Truly your <hi>Loſs is great;</hi> and unſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs, will be the <hi>ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravation</hi> of it: while your loſs is but your <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, unſenſibleneſſe</hi> will be your <hi>ſin.</hi> A ſin which God ſeverely ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madverts, though it do but relate to Saints of a more private ſtation; <hi>The righteous periſheth, and no man layeth it to heart, and merciful men are taken away, none
<pb facs="tcp:170519:5"/>conſidering that the righteous is taken away from the evil to come.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 57.1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This,
<note place="margin">Jer. 22.15, 16. 2 Chron. 34.3.35.23, 24.</note> ſome reſtrain to the perſon of <hi>JOSIAS,</hi> That <hi>righteous</hi> and <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful Prince:</hi> but, the words ſeem more general; being taken <hi>collectively,</hi> as <hi>Pſ. 11.5.</hi> And, without que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <hi>MANY godly ones,</hi> of that age, were taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by a <hi>premature death,</hi> and that, in a <hi>judicial ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity</hi> to the ſurviving ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of the <hi>profane</hi> &amp; hypocritical Iſraelites: who in the mean time gave themſelves to ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
<pb facs="tcp:170519:5"/>letting themſelves looſe to all ſenſual exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, And that, as it were under the <hi>protection</hi> of <hi>divine patience;</hi> taking Gods <hi>ſilence</hi> for Gods <hi>conſent,</hi> and his long-ſuffering towards them, as an infallible evidence of his <hi>approbation</hi> of their <hi>wickedneſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, if it were ſuch a ſin to over-look Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in the death of righteous and merciful <hi>men,</hi> what an aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of guilt is it, to be blind to the ſeverer diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations of juſtice, in
<pb facs="tcp:170519:6"/>the untimely death, of righteous and merciful <hi>Miniſters,</hi> whoſe lives are of a more publick and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal influence! Surely to ſhut our eyes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch ſignal indici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ums of divine diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, is highly provoking to God; and may juſtly bring a people, or a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, within the verge of that tremendous curſe. <hi>Becauſe they regard not the works of the Lord,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 28.5.</note> nor the operation of his hands, he will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them and not build them up.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:170519:6"/>
            <p>Secondly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Adv. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Lay to heart your great unthankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and unfruitfulneſs under ſuch precious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences.</hi> I am afraid, while ſome did <hi>deſpiſe</hi> his excellent labours, few did <hi>value</hi> them at a <hi>due rate.</hi> While ſome were fruitful onely in the <hi>works of the fleſh,</hi> not many did anſwer Gods expectations,
<note place="margin">Gal 5 2.</note> in <hi>the fruits of the ſpirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I accuſe none, I caution all; that while (poſſibly) you enquire into the cauſe of ſuch an <hi>unexpected ſtroke,</hi> every one may
<pb facs="tcp:170519:7"/>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1 King. 8.47. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> If they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to their heart.</note> 
               <hi>bethink themſelves,</hi> and cry with the Diſciples, <hi>Lord, is it I?</hi> Ah! Lord, was <hi>my murmuring, my unthankfulneſs, my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwerable converſation, my unrighteous oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> &amp;c. the cauſe of this ſore diſpleaſure? <hi>That which I ſee not,
<note place="margin">Job 34.3.</note> ſhew thou me; and, if I have done wickedly, I will do ſo no more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Adv. </seg>3</label> 
               <hi>Seek the face of God in faſting and prayer, TOGETHER and APART,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Zech. 12 12.</note> for the <hi>attoning</hi> of his <hi>favour,</hi> and the <hi>recruiting</hi> of your
<pb facs="tcp:170519:7"/>
               <hi>loſs.
<note place="margin">Numb. 2.14.</note> Had but her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpit in her face; ſhould ſhe not be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ſeven daies?</hi> Said God to <hi>Moſes</hi> concerning his <hi>murmuring Siſter.</hi> Dear Chriſtians, God hath done more then ſpit in your face,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ. 6.13.</hi> Bern. <hi>told his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, A rough hewen ſouldier, ſlighting his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofes, pointing to his ſide,</hi> One day a Spear ſhall make way to thine heart, for counſel to enter.</note> in this ſad diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation; he hath <hi>ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten</hi> you, and <hi>made him ſick in ſmiting you;</hi> God, by this <hi>wound</hi> make way for his word to enter into your hearts. You have cauſe to lye in the duſt, &amp; ſhame your ſelves in Gods preſence; as to deprecate (with <hi>tender-hearted</hi> Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah,)
<pb facs="tcp:170519:8"/>the <hi>wrath</hi> of God; ſo to get your <hi>breach repair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> And ſurely the <hi>recruit</hi> of ſuch <hi>a loſs</hi> is worth <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny daies</hi> of <hi>humiliation:</hi> and the Lord accept of your faces in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>I would faign have the <hi>name</hi> of Him, that ſhall be your Miniſter,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1 Sam. 1.20.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>q.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Asked, <hi>or</hi> Lent <hi>of Cod.</hi>
               </note> be <hi>SAMUEL.</hi> Holy <hi>Hannah</hi> will expound to you the myſtery; <hi>She called her ſon Samuel;</hi> and why? <hi>Becauſe,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked him of the Lord.</hi> This will be your <hi>comfort</hi> and your <hi>honour;</hi> That, when you ſee a faithfull
<pb facs="tcp:170519:8"/>Miniſter in your Pulpit, you may be able to ſay, <hi>This is He, whom we have begged of God:</hi> A mercy got by prayer, is <hi>a double mercy: a bleſſing</hi> and the <hi>return of prayer too;</hi> which, whatever the bleſſing be, is <hi>twice ſo much.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Adv. </seg>4</label> And, that you may proſper in your choice, let me humbly begg of you, <hi>to forget all your own private opinions and differences; Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions</hi> have been the ſad <hi>obſtructions</hi> of Englands <hi>Reformation</hi> and <hi>Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> I am confident
<pb facs="tcp:170519:9"/>had it not been for our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy <hi>diſſents,</hi> and more unhappy <hi>diſſentions,</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land had been the moſt glorious people upon the face of the earth, ſince Chriſt and his Apoſtles left the world: <hi>For the diviſions of Reuben are great ſearchings of heart.</hi> Of which we may ſay as it was ſaid once of the contentions between the Reformed Churches in <hi>Luthers</hi> time;
<note n="*" place="margin">Diſſenſus condonart poteſt, modo adſit fides in Chriſto; Diſſenſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes vero, neque ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanguinem fundamus, expiabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanct.</hi> to <hi>Luther.</hi>
               </note> Our <hi>DIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SENTS had been par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable</hi> (I ſpeak in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to matters of Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline,) <hi>through faith in Chriſt; but, as for our
<pb facs="tcp:170519:9"/>DISSENTIONS, all the blood in our veins will never waſh off the guilt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is time for Chriſtians to <hi>cloſe,</hi> and to make up their breaches. Is not Religion, <hi>tantum non,</hi> deſtroyed by our diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? Ah! that all ſuch as love Jeſus Chriſt in <hi>CHATHAM</hi> would here in be exemplary; that you would lay by all your differences, and animoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and unite, as <hi>one man,</hi> in this work, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the glory of God, the honour of the Goſpel, your good, and the good of your poſterity is ſo highly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned;
<pb facs="tcp:170519:10"/>
               <hi>the choiſe of a Miniſter.</hi> And, for the guiding of your choiſe, propound to your ſelves, I beſeech you, ſome ſuch <hi>Scripture-qualifications;</hi> as follow.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> Let him be <hi>a learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man:</hi> I am confident it is one of the policies of Antichriſt amongſt us, To cry down learning, as knowing that an <hi>ignorant</hi> and <hi>illiterate Miniſtry</hi> would eaſily betray the Proteſtant Religion into his hands; Who ſhould not be able to diſcover their impoſtures, nor evade their Sophiſtry. I do
<pb facs="tcp:170519:10"/>verily believe none are <hi>enemies</hi> to <hi>learning,
<note place="margin">Latrones prius lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>padem ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguunt &amp; tunc latroci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantur.</note> but</hi> ſuch as are <hi>friends</hi> to that <hi>deſign. Moſes</hi> was skil'd in all the learning of the Egyptians; Saint <hi>Paul</hi> brought up at <hi>the feet of Gamaliel,</hi> and, verſt in Heathen learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; he was able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute them out of their own
<note n="*" place="margin">Aratus. <hi>Act. 17.28.</hi> Anacrcon. <hi>1 Cor. 15.32.</hi> Menader. <hi>verſ. 33.</hi> Epimenides <hi>Tit 1.12 Whom the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Poets.</hi> The Pontificians have felt the dint of your <hi>Learned-Proteſtant Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries</hi> ſword; and, therefore, now would act the Philiſtines plot upon us,
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 13.19.</note> that there ſhould be no Smith found in all
<pb facs="tcp:170519:11"/>theſe three Nations; <hi>leſt they ſhould make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſwords and ſpears,</hi> weapons of <hi>defence,</hi> and <hi>offence,</hi> to ſtand up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their <hi>Babylonian</hi> forces. At leaſt, it is ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance that loves igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and <hi>errour</hi> that ſhuns the light.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Qual. </seg>2</label> He muſt be alſo a man of <hi>a ſound judgement,</hi> and well verſt in the <hi>Controverſies of the times,</hi> that ſo he may not only, be able to <hi>preach truth;</hi> but, to <hi>confute er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 1.9.</note> and <hi>convince the gain-ſayer:</hi> One that may
<pb facs="tcp:170519:11"/>be able to <hi>ſtop the mouth</hi> of ſeducers;
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> to
<note n="*" place="margin">Tit. 1.11.</note> 
               <hi>muz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zle</hi> them (as the word ſignifieth) that they may not, boldly,
<note place="margin">The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils words to Him were theſe; What ſtand I talking with thee? All men know thou art <hi>bold Rothwell,</hi> and fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, nor careſt for words; therefore I will talk with thee no more. See the life of Mr. <hi>Roth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> ſet forth by M. <hi>S. Clerk.</hi>
               </note> and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly, bark againſt the truth. Such an one was your late, and worthy, <hi>ROSWELL;</hi> the ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of the Hereticks, of this generation: The He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks were as much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of his name, as the <hi>Devil</hi> in poor poſſeſſed <hi>JOHN FOX</hi> of <hi>Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingham-ſhire</hi> was lately of a man of a <hi>like name,</hi> and Spirit; famous <hi>ROTHWELL.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:170519:12"/>
            <p>Thirdly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Qual. </seg>3</label> Be ſure to make choice of an <hi>holy man;</hi> a man whoſe life may be a <hi>Continual Sermon;</hi> that may <hi>teach</hi> by his <hi>converſation</hi> as well as by his <hi>doctrine. He hath no life in his doctrine that hath not doctrine, in his life:</hi> Nay, there is not a readier way to make men turn <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> then for a Miniſter to <hi>preach ſtrictly,</hi> and <hi>live looſely:</hi> Men will believe their <hi>eyes,</hi> rather then their <hi>ears;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vivitur exemplo.</note> and are lead by <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample</hi> rather then by <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept;</hi> whereby it cometh
<pb facs="tcp:170519:12"/>to paſs <hi>that the ſins of the teachers are the teachers of ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Qual. </seg>4</label> Make choiſe of a man of an <hi>healing Spirit;</hi> to which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired much <hi>prudence</hi> and <hi>integrity. Prudence;</hi> every fool can <hi>make</hi> diviſions; it is onely the <hi>wiſe man</hi> that can <hi>make them up.</hi> And there muſt be <hi>integrity</hi> too, leaſt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of healing diviſions, he comply with mens luſts, and ſerve the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the Devil, rather then of Jeſus Chriſt: as too many of our times do,
<pb facs="tcp:170519:13"/>who would have the repute of <hi>ſweet-ſpirited men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, A man there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of <hi>gravity</hi> and <hi>expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience</hi> would be much deſired among you. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Qual. </seg>5</label> 
               <hi>Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of fancy,</hi> is rarely joined (eſpecially in young men) with <hi>ſoundneſs of judgment:</hi> He that will do good in <hi>CHATHAM</hi> muſt carry ſome authority in his very <hi>perſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether my advice to you in theſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars may not come too late, I know not; if you have prevented me herein, I ſhall count it la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb facs="tcp:170519:13"/>
               <hi>well loſt:</hi> if not, I pray God, it may be a labour <hi>well beſtowed.</hi> And, <hi>The God of the Spirits of all fleſh ſet SUCH A MAN over your Congregation,
<note place="margin">Numb. 27.16, 17.</note> that may go in and out before you:</hi> that the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the Lord (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven while you may have a <hi>preacher) may not be as ſheep without a ſhepherd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, For his bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter encouragement, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Adv. </seg>5</label> 
               <hi>raiſe a competent proviſion for his comfortable ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence:</hi> that while he ſhould be <hi>ſtudying</hi> for
<pb facs="tcp:170519:14"/>your <hi>Souls,</hi> he may not be <hi>diſtracted</hi> with <hi>cares</hi> for his own <hi>Family.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the divinity of our times, That the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel muſt live upon the <hi>Contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the people;</hi> the people may indent with him for his <hi>work,</hi> but he muſt not indent with them for his <hi>wages;</hi> he muſt <hi>be bound,</hi> but they be <hi>free:</hi> and I would they were <hi>free</hi> indeed. An ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, which theſe times have found out, to tye up the Miniſters tongue un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their girdles: <hi>flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:170519:14"/>by this means may, probably, ſcrape out a <hi>live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyhood;</hi> but, <hi>faithful ones</hi> (without ſpecial provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence) are likely to be <hi>ſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; They hate him that reproveth in the gate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is in the power of your hand to prevent this miſchief. I know not any Congregation, of that qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, in England, wherein it is a matter of <hi>more faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> &amp; <hi>leſs charge,</hi> to raiſe up a <hi>liberal ſubſiſtence</hi> for a faithful Miniſter, then your <hi>CHATHAM</hi> is. (I know what I ſay;) Worthy Friends, make not
<pb facs="tcp:170519:15"/>your Miniſter an <hi>Almes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> that the poor man dare not to reprove ſin leſt one of <hi>my Maſters</hi> withdraw his contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. In this ſence I would have him be an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent;</hi> that he may ſpeak the truth of God without <hi>fear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Adv. </seg>6</label> Forget not the <hi>labour of love,</hi> and <hi>the work of faith,</hi> of <hi>Him</hi> that now is at <hi>reſt with God:</hi> His dear and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious <hi>Relicts</hi> are yet with you; what He is not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of in <hi>perſon,</hi> pay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his <hi>poſterity:</hi> It is
<pb facs="tcp:170519:15"/>but a <hi>ſmall matter,</hi> when you have reapt of the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Spirituals,</hi> that his <hi>Orphan-Family partake of your temporals:</hi> He was content to leave them poor, that he might make you rich; in the midſt of your <hi>riches,</hi> let not his precious relations remain <hi>poor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, my requeſt to you is, That you will own this <hi>vindication</hi> of his great faithfulneſs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity among you; and give it a room in your <hi>houſes,</hi> and in your <hi>hearts.</hi> Surely, you have the moſt
<pb facs="tcp:170519:16"/>right to this dedication, of any people in the world; in the ſervice of whoſe faith he ſpent his <hi>Eſtate,</hi> and <hi>Himſelf</hi> to boot. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it, as a Teſtimony of my dear and deſerved re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the <hi>Dead,</hi> and of my tender affection to the <hi>living;</hi> And the Lord add his own <hi>bleſſing:</hi> That the <hi>fruit</hi> of theſe poor la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours may be abundant, <hi>by many Thankſ-givings,</hi> to the glory of God. So Prayeth</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your very faithful, and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionate friend and ſervant in the Goſpel THO. CASE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170519:16"/>
            <head>
               <hi>ELIAH'S</hi> ABATEMENT: Or, CORRUPTION In the <hi>SAINTS.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>James 5.17.</hi>
                  </bibl> Elias was a man ſubject to like paſſions as we are; and he prayed earneſtly that it might not rain, and it rained not upon the earth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And he prayed again, and the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven gave rain.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THe words are a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration or evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the power and efficacy of prayer; That <hi>prayer rightly managed can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not want ſucceſs.</hi> The inſtance is taken from <hi>Elias;</hi> of what prevalency his prayers were
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170519:17"/>with God; the influences of the Heavens were bound up in his prayers, <hi>It raineth not,</hi> and <hi>raineth,</hi> as Elias <hi>will. He prayed earneſtly,
<note place="margin">Vir iſte potuit quod voluit.</note> and it rained not,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And he prayed again, and the Heavens gave rain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Elias,</hi> might ſome one ſay: Yea, He, indeed, might do much with God; a mighty Prophet, a man of eminent holineſs, and of high acquaintance with God; a <hi>Favourite</hi> of Heaven, <hi>à Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioribus,</hi> one of Gods <hi>privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours</hi> (as it were:) no wonder if his prayers were of ſuch po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency with the Almighty: But I am no <hi>Elias,</hi> but a poor ſinful creature, preſſed down with a double weight, a body of <hi>fleſh,</hi> and a body of <hi>ſin:</hi> and ſhall the prayers of ſuch a weak ſinful wretch as I am, find acceſs to, or acceptance with, the Holy God?</p>
            <p>To obviate this objection, and to remove this diſcouragement out of the minds of poor ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170519:17"/>ſenſible of their own un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſs, the Holy Ghoſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth a clauſe, or note of <hi>minora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> or <hi>abatement</hi> to <hi>Elias</hi> his Name: whereby he gives us to underſtand, that <hi>Elias</hi> was not heard ſo much for his <hi>Sanctity,</hi> as for his <hi>Sincerity;</hi> not for his own <hi>merit,</hi> but for the <hi>gracious reſpect</hi> which God beareth to the <hi>prayers</hi> of his people. He was indeed <hi>full of grace,</hi> highly favoured with the Lord: but he was neither <hi>God,</hi> nor <hi>Angel;</hi> he was <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but <hi>a man, Elias was a man.</hi> And a man he was, not exempt from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law of <hi>humane frailty.</hi> He had his <hi>infirmities,</hi> as well as other of the Saints of God, he was <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>of like paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions with us;</hi> like unto us in all things, <hi>ſin it ſelf not excepted.</hi> Hereupon inferring, that <hi>infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities</hi> in the meaneſt of Gods Saints, ſhal no more prejudice the acceptance and ſucceſs of their prayers with God then
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170519:18"/>they did in <hi>Elias</hi> himſelf. <hi>Elias was a man ſubject to like paſſions aſ we are, and he prayed earneſtly that it might not rain, and it rained not, &amp;c. And he prayed again, and the Heavens gave ſhowers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>— <hi>Subject to like paſſions as we are.]</hi> The word <hi>paſſion</hi> doth ſometimes ſignify onely the <hi>affections</hi> and <hi>motions</hi> of the mind, implanted in natures which in themſelves are neither <hi>morally</hi> good or evil; but as they are ſet upon their <hi>objects</hi> and are acted upon them in a <hi>regular</hi> or <hi>irregular manner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sometime <hi>Paſſions</hi> ſignify <hi>ſinful infirmities; ſinful perturba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of the mind.</p>
            <p>And ſometime <hi>paſſion</hi> is taken more <hi>ſtrictly</hi> for the ſpecial affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>anger</hi> and <hi>wrath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this place it may very well be extended to all: in my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe I ſhall manage it ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the two latter references, and in the <hi>doctrinal part,</hi> more <hi>largely,</hi> as importing <hi>ſinful per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbations;</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:170519:18"/>in the application to our <hi>preſent occaſion,</hi> to the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular paſſion of <hi>anger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſhall handle it in the larger ſignification of <hi>ſinful per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbations;</hi> which, without injury to this holy Prophet, we may un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand are aſcribed to him, by the Holy Ghoſt in this place: and that firſt, becauſe <hi>Elias</hi> is here called a <hi>Man;</hi> and ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe level'd with the reſt of the ſons and daughters of men, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>of like paſſions with us.</hi> The ſame minoration and abatement which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> uſeth to reſtrain the ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious <hi>Lyſtrians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 14. from verſ. 11. to verſ. 16. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> from giving him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and <hi>Barnabas divine worſhip,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Sirs, why do ye theſe things? we alſo are men of like paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions with you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo this inſtance in the Text, joined with this parallel of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> men of eminent holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; will warrant this general Obſervation;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The beſt of Gods Saints and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170519:19"/>Servants, have not onely their</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, <hi>but their</hi> ſinful <hi>infirmities and perturbations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ſad truth is of that <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal experience,</hi> that it would be as impoſſible as it is needleſs to make an <hi>induction</hi> of <hi>particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</hi> I ſhall onely therefore adde this <hi>Aggravation</hi> to make the obſervation more impreſſive; ſc. that, <hi>The greateſt paſſions and infirmities which the Saints have diſcovered, have been in thoſe very things wherein they have been moſt celebrated for the emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence of their graces.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abraham</hi> his eminence above other Saints, was in the grace of <hi>Faith.</hi> Whence he is called <hi>the father of the faithful;</hi> as much above other believers in faith, as the father is above the reſt of the Family, in dignity and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. He is ſet forth as the <hi>ſtandard</hi> and <hi>exemplar</hi> to all the <hi>Children of promiſe;</hi> and yet his eminent infirmity was <hi>infidelity;</hi> he ſtumbled twice upon the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170519:19"/>threſhold of <hi>unbelief,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding God had priviledged him with a promiſe of his <hi>ſpecial preſence and protection;</hi> Say, I pray thee, (<hi>Gen.</hi> 12.13. and 20.2.) <hi>Thou art my ſiſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Iſaac,</hi> the <hi>ſon,</hi> not of his <hi>loins</hi> more then of his <hi>infirmities,</hi> halt's upon the ſame foot in the like temptation, <hi>Gen.</hi> 26.7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes,</hi> the <hi>Man of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 12.7, 8.</note> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured above all other <hi>mortals</hi> with the <hi>beatifical viſion</hi> on this ſide glory: yet even <hi>Him</hi> we finde miſcarrying through <hi>unbelief,</hi> when upon the <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of God</hi> to give <hi>fleſh</hi> to the people, his faith was ſo <hi>low,</hi> that it could riſe no higher then <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond cauſes:
<note place="margin">2 King. 7.1, 2.</note> Shall the flocks and herds be ſlain for them?</hi> not much better under that tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then ſometime <hi>Ahabs Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> who becauſe he could not ſee <hi>proviſion</hi> enough <hi>on earth</hi> to accompliſh the propheſie of <hi>plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in Samaria,</hi> (under ſuch an extreme exigence as it was then
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170519:20"/>reduced unto) thought <hi>there was not enough in Heaven; If the Lord ſhould open windows in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, might this thing be?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> to whom God gave once this honourable teſtimony, <hi>A man after mine own heart:</hi> Yet afterward left a double blot upon his name, <hi>Adultery</hi> and <hi>Murder;</hi> firſt he polluted <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riahs</hi> bed, and afterward ſtained his hands in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riahs</hi> blood.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ye have heard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jam. 5.11.</note> ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>of the patience of Job;</hi> Yea, and we have heard of his impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience too; how, in the anguiſh of his ſpirit, <hi>he curſed the day of his birth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job. 3.1.</note> with a bitter curſe. And ſo did another famous Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet of God after him, <hi>Jeremiah</hi> Chap. 20.14.</p>
            <p>Into what an <hi>exceſs of paſſion</hi> did <hi>Jonas</hi> (an holy Prophet of God without queſtion) chafe himſelf, when, conteſting with his Maker, he is not afraid to anſwer that meek queſtion, <hi>doſt thou well to be angry?</hi> with that tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendous
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170519:20"/>inſolence; <hi>Yea, I do well to be angry, even unto death?
<note place="margin">Jonah 4.9</note> Jonah</hi> was <hi>angry</hi> becauſe <hi>God</hi> was <hi>patient;</hi> but it was well for <hi>Jonah,</hi> that he had to do with ſo patient a God, or elſe God had deſtroyed <hi>Jonas</hi> inſtead of <hi>Nineveh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter,</hi> who thought his <hi>love</hi> to Chriſt as <hi>ſtrong as death,</hi> and his zeal as <hi>cruel</hi> as the <hi>grave,</hi> under a ſurpriſe of <hi>fear,</hi> not onely <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſakes</hi> his Lord, but <hi>forſwears</hi> him alſo. And what ſhall I ſay more? for the time would fail me to tell you of <hi>Gedeon,</hi> and of <hi>Barak,</hi> and of <hi>Sampſon,</hi> and of <hi>Jephtah,</hi> of <hi>Samuel</hi> alſo, and of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets; All who, though emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Servants and Favourites of God, yet, have left the veſtigia's, and <hi>prints</hi> of their eminent infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities behind them, all witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to this ſad truth that they were <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>men ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to like paſſions as we are.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Elias,</hi> here, a ſeraphical Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, of whom glorious things
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170519:21"/>are ſpoken in Scripture, He rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the dead, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 4.34. &amp;c. ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth fire from heaven againſt the <hi>Prieſts of Baal.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 18.18. 1 Kings 19.8. 1 Kings 1.10.</note> He could live forty dayes and forty nights without food; ſnatcht fire from heaven, on the Captains of two fifties, and their companies; was fed by Ravens; carried up to heaven in a fiery Chariot. He was of that prevalency with God, that his prayers could ſhut and open heaven at his pleaſure, as in the Text, &amp;c. Even this <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah</hi> was not without his <hi>natural</hi> and his <hi>ſinful</hi> infirmities; He was an <hi>hungry,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 17.11. yea he was ſurprized with the <hi>fear of death,</hi> and under that fear <hi>flieth from the face of Jeza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel:</hi> he that feared not <hi>a potent King,</hi> ſurrounded with 450 ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and a numerous multitude of Apoſtate <hi>ſubjects;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Flictus ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſo imbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilior.</note> Yet now, as if it had not been the <hi>ſame Elijah,</hi> flyeth from the face of a <hi>woman.</hi> He that had <hi>faith</hi> enough to cauſe 450. ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170519:21"/>Prieſts to be put to death, begins now to ſink under the <hi>fear of death</hi> himſelf; yea, through <hi>impatience</hi> of ſpirit, <hi>requeſts to die;</hi> and, as if it had been but a <hi>ſtrein of humility,</hi> maketh this his apology,
<note place="margin">1 King. 19.4.</note> 
               <hi>For I am not better then my Fathers.</hi> In a word, all kind of infirmities incident unto man, are here aſcribed to Him by the ſpirit of God.</p>
            <p>More inſtances might be called in; but theſe are ſufficient to witneſſe this ſad truth, that, <hi>The beſt of men, are but men at the beſt; Saints have their infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> the thing it ſelf being ſo univerſal an experience.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>What may be the <hi>Grounds</hi> or <hi>Reaſons</hi> of the point? <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Grounds. </seg>
                  </label> 
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt is, <hi>Saints and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners are all one mans Sons;</hi> we are all tainted in our <hi>Original,</hi> and deeply poyſoned with the venom of <hi>Adams</hi> firſt tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: The Nature which we have traduced from his loynes, is a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170519:22"/>
                  <hi>Dung-hill</hi> full of <hi>Vermin;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Omnis ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guis conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor.</hi> Petr.</note> a <hi>Sea</hi> full of <hi>Monſters;</hi> an <hi>hell</hi> full of <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean ſpirits:</hi> a very <hi>bottomleſſe pit of corruption.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Petr.</note> All blood is of a colour. And though in Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, the <hi>new creature</hi> is made <hi>partaker of the divine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.4</note> yet it is not with the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter abolition of the <hi>Old man.</hi> In Converſion, Corruption is <hi>morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,</hi> but not <hi>annihilated:</hi> the <hi>Covenant of Grace</hi> hath taken or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for the <hi>conquering</hi> of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, not for the <hi>extinction</hi> of it; <hi>Sin ſhall not reign.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 6.12.</note> Bleſſed be God for that, till more comes. And bleſſed be God, the time is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing when it ſhall not <hi>be;</hi> ſin ſhall not be <hi>caſt down</hi> only, but caſt out; not loſe its <hi>dominion</hi> only, but its <hi>entity</hi> and <hi>exiſtence.</hi> In the mean time, the beſt of Saints car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry about them a <hi>body of death;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 7.24. Rom. 8.7.</note> the <hi>remains</hi> of a curſed <hi>enmity</hi> againſt God, which makes them weary of themſelves, and willing to groan their very lives out with their complaints.
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Oh wretch that I
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170519:22"/>am, who ſhall deliver me!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is true, <hi>They that are Chriſts,
<note place="margin">Gal. 5.24.</note> have crucified the fleſh with its affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and luſts;</hi> yet, ſo notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, as that <hi>ſin</hi> preſently <hi>giveth not up the Ghoſt:</hi> Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and nature in the Saints breathe out their <hi>laſt</hi> together, and are not buried, but in one and the ſame grave.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Reaſon.</hi> God will have it ſo, <hi>to keep the Saints in continual exerciſe.</hi> The infirmities of the Saints find them work: <hi>weeping</hi> work, <hi>groaning</hi> work, <hi>ſighing</hi> work: hence is their life called a <hi>warfare</hi> in Scripture.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Ground</hi> or <hi>Reaſon.</hi> More parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly, <hi>grace ſometimes meets with an ill nature:</hi> I mean, the <hi>Second</hi> nature, <hi>Conſtitution.</hi> All the ſons and daughters of <hi>Adam</hi> are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually depraved and corrupted by their <hi>firſt</hi> common nature, drawne from his loynes: but that vitioſity is differently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined and acted by their <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170519:23"/>nature,</hi> which is nothing elſe but their <hi>complexion</hi> and <hi>temper</hi> derived from their next immediate parents: whereby one is inclined to <hi>this</hi> ſin, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to <hi>that</hi> ſin; one to <hi>Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> another to <hi>paſſion;</hi> a third to <hi>uncleanneſſe,</hi> &amp;c. more to one then to another, according to the predominancie of the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour in their individual conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turtions.</p>
               <p>Nor is this <hi>hereditary vitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity</hi> altogether aboliſhed, though much <hi>corrected</hi> by ſuperveniency of <hi>Grace:</hi> And with ſuch an evill <hi>bent</hi> and <hi>diſpoſition</hi> doth God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo leave his own children to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict many times, in them to make <hi>experiments</hi> to the world of the <hi>efficacy of Grace,</hi> what <hi>excellent veſſels</hi> Jeſus Chriſt can make of <hi>knotty</hi> and worm-eaten materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als: according to his anſwer to the Apoſtle,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.9</note> 
                  <hi>My grace ſhall be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for thee.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:170519:23"/>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
               <p>Firſt for Caution.</p>
               <p>In the firſt place, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Caut. </seg>1</label> Take heed <hi>of abuſing theſe inſtances of the Saints infirmities to lewd and wicked purpoſes,</hi> encouragements to ſin. Say not in thine heart, why may not I be <hi>overtaken with wine</hi> as well as <hi>Noah? impatient</hi> as well as <hi>Job?</hi> commit adultery as well as <hi>David?</hi> be paſſionate as well as <hi>Elias</hi> and <hi>Jonah,</hi> Prophets of God?</p>
               <p>Nay, but, oh man, who ever thou art, theſe failings &amp; infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Saints were not left out in Scripture for <hi>encouragement,</hi> but for <hi>Caution:</hi> they are not our <hi>Land-marks,</hi> but our <hi>Sea-marks,</hi> our <hi>Fire-lights</hi> in this <hi>dark world,</hi> crying to us afar off (as it were) Take heed, here is a <hi>Quick-ſand,</hi> there's a <hi>Rock;</hi> and, here <hi>David</hi> was like to ſuffer <hi>ſhipwrack, Job</hi> ran a <hi>ground,</hi> and <hi>Jonas</hi> was like to be <hi>caſt away,</hi> &amp; ſic in coeteris. The Apoſtle tells us as much.</p>
               <p>Now theſe things are our <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:170519:24"/>or <hi>Types:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.6.11. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Examples, but not for our <hi>imitation,</hi> but for our <hi>admonition, upon whom the ends of the world are come;</hi> to <hi>the intent</hi> that we ſhould not be <hi>ſurpriſed</hi> with temptation, as <hi>Noah</hi> and <hi>David</hi> were ſurpriſed, <hi>neither</hi> be <hi>impatient</hi> as <hi>Job</hi> and <hi>Jeremy</hi> were impatient, <hi>nor paſſionate,</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> were paſſionate.</p>
               <p>He that, upon theſe accompts, ſhould take liberty for the fleſh, and indulge ſinful diſpoſitions, perverteth the gracious purpoſes of Scripture, and makes God the <hi>patron of ſin,</hi> by interpretation. And therefore take heed to your own ſpirits.</p>
               <p>If the beſt of Saints have their infirmities and ſinful perturbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Cant. </seg>2</label> Take heed of <hi>Cenſuring them for their failings.</hi> The world condemns the generation of Gods children for cenſuring others, while there are no ſuch cenſorious perſons upon the face of the earth, as themſelves.</p>
               <p>If a profeſſor of Religion do
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170519:24"/>but <hi>ſlip,</hi> it is a <hi>fall;</hi> and if he fall, it is a fall of <hi>hypocriſie,</hi> not of <hi>infirmity:</hi> while they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves do live, and lye, and wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in ſin, and allow them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in all manner of bruitiſh exceſſes, they do moſt unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably judge and condemn the Saints, for their failings and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Their own groſs ſins</hi> muſt paſſe for <hi>infirmities,</hi> but the <hi>Saints infirmities</hi> muſt be cenſured as <hi>groſs ſins:</hi> yea, not only the <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> but the whole <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> muſt ſuffer for it; <q rend="inline">I, theſe are your <hi>profeſſors,</hi> theſe be your <hi>Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans,</hi> your <hi>Preciſians,</hi> they are <hi>all hypocrites,</hi> never a <hi>barrel better herring.</hi>
                  </q> God ſhall ſmite ſuch <hi>whited walls,</hi> who under the pretence of <hi>Law,</hi> judge their brethren <hi>contrary to Law;</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the <hi>Law of ecuity,</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the <hi>Law of Charity,</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that <hi>royal Law,
<note place="margin">Mat. 7.12.</note> What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ye would that men ſhould do unto you, do ye even ſo to them;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170519:25"/>for this is the Law and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chriſtians, remember the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God (whileſt in the fleſh) they are <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of like paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, with other men; when they put on the <hi>Saint,</hi> they do not put off the <hi>Man;</hi> and when they begin to be <hi>Spirit,</hi> they do not ceaſe to be <hi>fleſh. The beſt of men are but men at the beſt.</hi> Remember they carry about them the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainders of <hi>original corruption;</hi> and many times their next Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents bequeath them a wretched Legacy of an ill <hi>Conſtitution;</hi> a <hi>paſſionate</hi> nature, a <hi>timorous</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, a <hi>cloſe tenacious</hi> nature, &amp;c. upon which accompts, every piece is to be allowed his grains: which if we deny, we <hi>ſin</hi> againſt <hi>God;</hi> and <hi>wrong</hi> the <hi>generation of his children,</hi> Pſal. 73.15.</p>
               <p>It is a moſt unrighteous parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality, in the men of the world to juſtify themſelves in <hi>habitual reigning ſinnes,</hi> and to judge the children of light, for their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170519:25"/>
                  <hi>dwelling,</hi> and but <hi>rare</hi> infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities.</p>
               <p>Chriſtians at large do inſult over a few <hi>ſtrict ones</hi> for their failings, <hi>quaſi de ipſa juſtitia,</hi> (as one ſayes) as if they were ſitting in judgement upon <hi>holineſſe it ſelf;</hi> and ſo every day Chriſt hath many Martyrs.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <label>Queſt.</label> 
                     <hi>But how may a man know whether</hi> ſinful diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, <hi>be but</hi> dwelling in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities; <hi>or indeed reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſins? or how may they be</hi> diſtinguiſhed?</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>Anſw.</label> The Anſwer to this queſtion, will lead us to a ſecond Uſe.</p>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An Uſe of <hi>Examination.</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>2</label> In which for your help, let me give you theſe Marks and Signs.</head>
               <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Evidence of Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</hi>
                  </note> ſinful perturbations are then but <hi>infirmities, when accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with converting grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Corruption in the men of the world ſprings from an <hi>unmorti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170519:26"/>root,
<note place="margin">Deut. 29.28. Roſh, <hi>ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly an head, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly, a poyſonous leafe.</hi>
                     </note> a root of bitterneſſe,</hi> as the Scripture calls it; or a <hi>root bringing forth a poyſonful leafe:</hi> original ſin is whole in every un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate perſon, whereby it erecteth a full power and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; further then as it is <hi>reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> by an external power. Sin is in every unconverted man and woman, as <hi>Rex in regno; as a King in his throne;</hi> upon which accompt no ſin that an <hi>unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> perſon committeth, (though <hi>never ſo ſmall,</hi>) is to be reputed as a ſin of <hi>infirmity;</hi> but a <hi>reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> ſin; ſin in the full force and vigour of it; ſo far as the act extends.</p>
               <p>But the ſtrength of that cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed principle is <hi>cruſht</hi> and <hi>broken</hi> in regeneration; though <hi>Original ſin giveth not up the Ghoſt,</hi> at the inſtant of the forming of the new creature, yet it hath received that <hi>fatal blow,</hi> of which it ſhall never recover its priſtine ſtrength and activity.</p>
               <p>The failings of Gods people
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170519:26"/>proceed not from a <hi>want of Grace,</hi> but only from a want <hi>in</hi> Grace and that is properly called <hi>infirmity;</hi> Some <hi>weakneſſe and debility</hi> in the <hi>reſiſting faculty,</hi> whereby ſometimes grace it ſelf is <hi>ſurpriſed,</hi> and temptation gets <hi>the better,</hi> in the preſent aſſault. Make out therefore a work of grace, and the controverſie is determined; thy corruptions are but <hi>infirmities,</hi> and not <hi>preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; ſlaves,</hi> not <hi>Lords and Kings;</hi> if thy nature be changed.</p>
               <p>And this ſtrongly evinceth, that the ſins of the generality of thoſe that are called Chriſtians, are <hi>reigning ſins, thrones and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities</hi> in the ſoul, not onely becauſe they cannot evidence a work of grace in their heart up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any <hi>Scriptural accompt,</hi> (ſo poſſibly may not the <hi>New Convert</hi> by reaſon of the many <hi>fears</hi> and <hi>miſtakes,</hi> which darken his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding.) Therefore not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (I ſay) becauſe they <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not,</hi> but much more becauſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170519:27"/>they do not ſo much as <hi>go about ſuch work;</hi> they take up their intereſt in Chriſt <hi>upon truſt;</hi> and ſwim down the ſtream of <hi>ſecurity,</hi> thinking it enough to <hi>hope well,</hi> and to <hi>believe</hi> that they <hi>do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve:</hi> Whereas the new-crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>works out his Salvation with fear and trembling,
<note place="margin">Phil. 2.12.</note> and giveth all diligence to make his calling and Election ſure;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.10.</note> never giving God or his Soul reſt, till God give reſt to his Soul; in ſome <hi>Goſpel evidence</hi> and <hi>aſſurance</hi> of <hi>Chriſt in him, the hope of glory:</hi> And this very reſtleſneſs in the Soul is an evidence,
<note place="margin">Coloſ. 1.27.</note> in the <hi>abſence</hi> or <hi>dimneſs</hi> of other evidences.</p>
               <p>A ſecond Difference, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Diff. </seg>2</label> or Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing ſign, is this:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sinful diſtempers are then our infirmities, when they are our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions.</hi> Men accompt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>miſerable,</hi> becauſe of their infirmities in the natural life;
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Rom. 7.24.</note> and ſo do the Saints in the <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual: Oh! wretched man that I am:</hi> the word ſignifieth, a
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170519:27"/>man <hi>beſet</hi> with, or <hi>cruſhed</hi> under affliction and miſeries:
<note place="margin">ex <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſuffero, &amp; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, luctus.</note> the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of the Saints are matter of continual <hi>ſorrow and ſighing,</hi> cauſing them to go up and down as <hi>mourners</hi> in the world.</p>
               <p>Unregenerate people <hi>think never the worſe of themſelves</hi> for their ſinful diſtempers: their <hi>pride,</hi> their <hi>paſſion,</hi> their <hi>ſinful fears,</hi> their inordinate affections, their evil concupiſcences, &amp;c. they make them not to hold down their heads, or to look upon themſelves as <hi>miſerable.</hi> Groſs and ſcandalous ſins may trouble their conſciences ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times; but ſinful <hi>diſpoſitions,</hi> vitious <hi>habits,</hi> evil <hi>inclinations</hi> do not at all affect or afflict their Souls: They have learned to put all upon the ſcore of <hi>infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity;</hi> even their moſt <hi>bruitiſh affections,</hi> and fouleſt <hi>turpitudes;</hi> they are their <hi>infirmities;</hi> and <hi>no man is without his infirmities</hi> this is their <hi>Apology,</hi> and herein they acquieſce, and are no more trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:170519:28"/>
               <p>But <hi>gracions Souls</hi> go <hi>bowed down</hi> under their <hi>infirmities;</hi> they ſpread them before the Lord, and judge themſelves for them daily at Gods tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</p>
               <p>And this is a good ſign, they are but <hi>infirmities,</hi> and <hi>no more,</hi> they cannot bear them <hi>patiently: wo is me for my wound is grievous: my wounds ſtinck and are cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Carnal people plead for their luſts, and make Apologies for their corruptions; did ever any godly man do ſo? This is a ſign, it is more then <hi>infirmity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Third <hi>Evidence:</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Evid. </seg>3</label> In the next place; <hi>Corruption</hi> is then <hi>infirmity</hi> when we <hi>labour to have them cured:</hi> gracious Souls carry their ſpiritual diſtempers to the great <hi>Phyſician,</hi> with the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> his petition,
<note place="margin">Jer. 17.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Heal me O Lord, and I ſhall be healed.</hi> Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate perſons under a pang of conviction may go to God for <hi>pardon,</hi> but not for <hi>healing;</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:170519:28"/>they can live without a <hi>cure,</hi> though they cannot die without a <hi>pardon;</hi> Yea, let but the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt be a little alaid in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, they will quickly forget pardon alſo. This is that which I ſay; <hi>Quiet will ſatisfie a natural conſcience, nothing but cure</hi> wil ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy a renewed conſcience; and for this it ſtriveth, and this it purſueth to the very death: ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering any thing, and doing any thing, and denying it ſelf any thing, ſo it may have ſpiritual infirmity healed. It is a good ſign — paſſions are but infirmities, when Chriſtians are much in the duties of <hi>mortification: prayer,</hi> and <hi>faſting, meditation,</hi> &amp; <hi>mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; drawing power and influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence from Jeſus Chriſt his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and Sufferings, by vital acts of faith:</hi> with the holy Apoſtle, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.10. and <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.14.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>Evidential diff, Infirmities</hi> in the Saints, <hi>if no more,</hi> are <hi>medicinal;</hi> God makes uſe of their paſſions for the <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:170519:29"/>of corruption. The Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond is cut by a Diamond; Corruption is curative to Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption: God makes oil of ſcorpions: and turns poyſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into an antidote. As,</p>
               <p>Firſt, God makes uſe of the infirmities of the Saints to cure them of their <hi>Pride.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pride cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> The infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of the <hi>Children of promiſe, ſerve to keep them humble;</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the Goſpel or <hi>private Chriſtians:</hi> I am confident all the <hi>afflictions</hi> in the world are not ſo influential to the mortifying of their pride as their <hi>Corruptions:</hi> Whence an holy Miniſter of great eminence, both for <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>parts,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered a friend that demanded of him, what he did to keep his heart humble under ſuch emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent abilities? <hi>I will warrant you,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>I have corruptions enough to keep me humble.</hi> It was upon the ſame accompt that <hi>the great A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle of the Gentiles,</hi> was exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed with a <hi>thorn in his fleſh;</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:170519:29"/>(which ſome conceive to have been ſome <hi>inward extimulations of concupiſcence,)
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.12. <hi>A Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion edg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Trap. in locum.</note> leſt through the abundance of revelation,</hi> he ſhould have been <hi>exalted above mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is not ſo with the ungodly, they can <hi>ſwear</hi> and be <hi>proud</hi> too, be <hi>unclean</hi> and <hi>proud</hi> too; paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate and proud, worldly and proud, baſely <hi>fearful,</hi> and yet be proud, &amp; ſic in coeteris.</p>
               <p>This ſhews theſe diſtempers are <hi>reigning mortal diſeaſes;</hi> not <hi>infirmities</hi> in them.</p>
               <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">Gal. 6.1. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpicio</note> God by the ſence of ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempers, doth cure the Saints of <hi>Cenſoriouſneſs towards their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: Conſidering themſelves;</hi> or <hi>reflecting on themſelves,</hi> look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>into</hi> themſelves; looking <hi>through and through</hi> themſelves; <hi>round about,</hi> as the word ſignifies: And have not I my <hi>blemiſhes,</hi> my <hi>ſpots,</hi> my <hi>ſinful incumbrances?</hi> and ſhall <hi>I judge my brother,</hi> and <hi>condemn my brother?</hi> God forbid; how can I judge <hi>him</hi> and not
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170519:30"/>condemn <hi>my ſelf? who art thou that judgeſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea, the infirmities of the children of God, make them tender and compaſſionate, even towards wicked men, more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to <hi>pray</hi> for them then to <hi>inſult</hi> over them: ſo runs the Apoſtles advice,
<note place="margin">Tit. 2.2, 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Speak evil of no man, but be gentle, ſhewing all meekneſs unto all men:</hi> a great latitude and condeſcention! <hi>all meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> unto <hi>all men.</hi> And why? <hi>For we our ſelves were ſometimes fooliſh, diſobedient, deceivers, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving divers luſts and pleaſures.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aut fui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, aut ſumus, aut poſſnmus; eſſe quod hic eſt.</note> Ah! ſaith a gracious Soul, I <hi>am ſuch,</hi> or I have been ſuch, or I might have been ſuch as this drunkard, or this adulterer is, &amp;c. I have the <hi>ſeeds</hi> of all theſe depraved affections in my nature:
<note place="margin">Luk. 18.11.</note> The voice of a proud Phariſee, is, <hi>God I thank thee I am not as other men are; extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners, unjuſt, adulterers, or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as this Publicane:</hi> he ſeems to aſcribe the <hi>difference</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> but
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170519:30"/>indeed he arrogates it to <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf:</hi> his <hi>God I thank thee,</hi> is but a <hi>ſtirrop,</hi> whereby he mounts himſelf into the ſaddle of vain glory: and when he hath done, rides over his poor brother, and tramples him under feet with contempt &amp; ſcorn, <hi>this Publicane;</hi> this argueth, his heart was ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not with <hi>thankfulneſs,</hi> but with <hi>pride.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A child of God <hi>pitieth</hi> and <hi>prayeth</hi> for thoſe that are worſe then himſelf. Lord, pitty this <hi>poor drunkard;</hi> Lord, convince and humble this <hi>proud oppoſer,</hi> &amp; ſic in coeteris.</p>
               <p>And all this upon the accompt of <hi>Self;</hi> He conſidereth what he <hi>was,</hi> what he <hi>is,</hi> what he might be, <hi>left unto himſelf.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſus hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes alienae domus, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienarum rerum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpector.</hi> 1 Pet. 4.15.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The thing is this: he hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to do <hi>at home; Judging<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work</hi> enough to do there, and <hi>Condemning-work</hi> enough to do there; and therefore he dares not <hi>play the Biſhop in another mans dioceſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:170519:31"/>
               <p>It is a pretty criticiſm,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>otior, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guo.</hi> 1 Tim. 5.13. <hi>fuſt,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>and then</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>First they</hi> do not <hi>what they</hi> ſhould <hi>at</hi> home, <hi>and then they do</hi> more then they ſhould a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad.</note> that the ſame word in the Greek, which ſignifieth to <hi>cenſure,</hi> ſignifieth alſo to be <hi>idle,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying this much to us, that he that is ſo buſie abroad, is firſt idle at home: and that is the reaſon why true Saints are ſo ſparing in their cenſures, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God ſuffers their own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities to find them ſo much work at home, that they have little mind or leaſure to ſpend their ſeverities upon other men.</p>
               <p>They that cannot bear with infirmities in their brethren, <hi>ſay their prayers,</hi> with more <hi>pride</hi> then <hi>faith:</hi> ſurely we are to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low our fellow ſervants <hi>for</hi> their infirmities, though we are not to allow them <hi>in</hi> their infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities; God permits them <hi>a being</hi> in the choiſeſt of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, upon that very ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:170519:31"/>
               <p>Thirdly. By this meanes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, <hi>God weans his people from the love of the world.</hi> Look what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary <hi>ſore-preſſing afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> do upon men, made up only of <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Reaſon; that</hi> the <hi>ſence of Corruption</hi> doth upon the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; it makes them <hi>weary of the world,</hi> and forceth from them <hi>Davids</hi> complaint,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 20.5. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Haec ſunt quae homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes faciunt invitos mori.</hi> 2 Cor. 5.2, 3, 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Woe is me that I ſojourn in</hi> Meſech, <hi>and have my habitation in the tents of</hi> Keder: the Septuagint render it, Woe is me, <hi>that my pilgrimage is prolong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> Wicked men their luſts are ſo far from making weary of the world, that there is nothing makes them ſo unwilling to die. They would fain live for ever here, that they might ſin for ever. But under the burden of <hi>Corruption</hi> it is, that the Saints <hi>groan;</hi> die they would, that they might ſin no more.</p>
               <p>Other advantages there are which God makes of the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Corruption in the godly; but theſe may ſerve for a taſte,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170519:32"/>You may enlarge in your own meditations: by all which God expounds and fulfills <hi>Sampſons riddle</hi> to them, <hi>Out of the Eater comes meat, and out of the ſtrong comes ſweetneſſe.</hi> God maketh <hi>oyle</hi> of theſe <hi>ſcorpions</hi> and <hi>anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotes</hi> of <hi>poyſon.</hi> The Lord keep us from turning theſe <hi>antidotes</hi> into poyſon,
<note place="margin">Jude 4.</note> this <hi>grace of God into laſciviouſneſſe,</hi> this <hi>Doctrine of free grace</hi> into <hi>occaſions</hi> and <hi>ſnares</hi> for the <hi>fleſh:</hi> this were to imitate the Devil, not to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate God; God bringeth good out of evill, the Devill brings <hi>evill</hi> out of <hi>good.</hi> So it is with wicked men; that which they call <hi>infirmity,</hi> expoſeth them to <hi>temptation,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.13.</note> and is an encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to them to ſin; evil men and ſeducers grow worſe and worſe, deceiving, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Evidence. </seg>5</label> and being deceived.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A fifth evidential difference is this, the Prophets and ſervants of God, notwithſtanding their ſinful diſtempers, <hi>are very ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in their generations.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:170519:32"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> notwithſtanding his <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,</hi> of what a choyce influence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the people? <hi>How oft did he ſtand in the gap,</hi> to turn away the wrath of God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Job,</hi> notwithſtanding his fits of <hi>jmpatience,</hi> of what uſe? He was <hi>eyes</hi> to the <hi>blinde, feet</hi> to the <hi>lame.</hi> The poor mans <hi>Advocate</hi> in the gate to plead his cauſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>David,</hi> for all his ſlips &amp; ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, what a Reformer? what an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Ruler in his Kingdome? In his <hi>Family:</hi> Pſal. 101. <hi>per totum, &amp; ſic in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aeteris.</hi> Thus <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as,</hi> a man ſubject to <hi>paſſion,</hi> and yet what ſervice did he do for God? for his generation? wicked men, while full of <hi>luſts,</hi> are an uſeleſſe generation, good for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
<note place="margin">Mat 5.13.</note> (as our Lord ſaith of <hi>unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voury ſalt,) but to be caſt out, and trodden under foot of men.</hi> They are ſerviceable neither to God nor man: like the withered vine, of which you cannot make a pin to hang a <hi>veſſel</hi> on: they are of no <hi>ſupport</hi> or ſervice, meer <hi>Cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber-grounds</hi>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:170519:33"/>they are, and the place where they live longs for a vomit, to ſpew them out. Their <hi>ſins</hi> are <hi>reigning</hi> ſins: and they are meer ſlaves to their corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<note place="margin">Tit. 3.2, 3.</note> 
                  <hi>ſerving divers luſts and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures:</hi> Gods children, though they have their decayes and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble times; yet are like the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving vine, which brings forth fruit to make glad the heart of <hi>God and man.</hi> This ſpeaks no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in them but humane frailty.</p>
               <p>A ſixth and laſt differentiall note,
<note place="margin">6. Signall Difference.</note> Gods dear and precious ſervants, though full of infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, yet they <hi>are a praying peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:</hi> full of weakneſſes, but full of prayer too. Of <hi>Saul</hi> it is ſaid, As ſoon as ever converting grace took hold of his heart,
<note place="margin">Acts 9.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Behold he prayeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is the eminent inſtance in the Text.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Elias</hi> had his <hi>paſsions,</hi> but <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi> was a <hi>mighty man in prayer;</hi> he could ſhut and open heaven at
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170519:33"/>his pleaſure. He could do what he would with God, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: in praying,
<note place="margin">Rom. 12.</note> he pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: the righteous pray, and are <hi>fervent</hi> in prayer: their very infirmities ſet them a praying; to pray down their <hi>paſsions,</hi> and to pray out their ſinful diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers.</p>
               <p>Carnal perſons are full of paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, but empty of prayers; they can ſwear, but they cannot pray, they can curſe, but they cannot pray; <hi>ſay prayers</hi> poſſibly they may (as they call it) but they cannot <hi>make prayers;</hi> they may ſay <hi>Our Father, &amp;c.</hi> but they have not the <hi>ſpirit of adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> to cry <hi>Abba Father:</hi> to pour out their ſouls to God in child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſupplications and importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities.</p>
               <p>Yea ſome there be, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of making prayers, are more ready to <hi>Curſe</hi> prayer, <hi>&amp; tantum non,</hi> to <hi>blaſpheme the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of prayer</hi> in the children of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption. This evidences them to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170519:34"/>be under the power and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of ſin.</p>
               <p>And now to apply our ſelves and the Text,
<note place="margin">The Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> to the ſad occaſion before us, the death of our dear and Reverend brother; Mr. <hi>Walter Roſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I told you in the entrance, that beſides the two former acceptations of the word <hi>paſsions, ſc. natural affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> and <hi>ſinful perturbations;</hi> there was a third acception of the word, namely, as it denoteth more ſpecially <hi>the affection of wrath; ſudden</hi> and <hi>irregular Anger.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this the beſt of Gods Saints and ſervants have not been without.
<note place="margin">Numb. 20.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Moſes,</hi> whom be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you ſaw <hi>defective in faith,</hi> at another time you may behold <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive</hi> in his <hi>paſſion.</hi> He <hi>ſmiteth</hi> the <hi>rock,</hi> when he was but to <hi>ſpeak</hi> to it: and his anger maketh him <hi>double his ſtroke.</hi> He <hi>ſmote the rock twice.</hi> He <hi>revileth</hi> the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170519:34"/>when he ſhould have <hi>convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced them; hear ye Rebells.</hi> And, offended (as it ſeems) at his Commiſſion, he hardly forbeareth to <hi>murmur, muſt we bring water out of this rock? M<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ST WE?</hi> And thus while he ſmiteth <hi>water</hi> out of the <hi>rock,</hi> he ſtriketh <hi>fire</hi> out of his own <hi>heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Behold and tremble,
<note place="margin">Numb. 12.3.</note> The <hi>meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt man upon the face of the earth</hi> is tranſported into paſſion, and his paſſion hurrieth him into ſuch <hi>indecencies,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Numb 20.12.</note> that hereupon God denieth him <hi>entrance into the land of Promiſe;</hi> The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> whom he brought out of Egypt, <hi>could not enter in becauſe of their</hi> unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, and <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf muſt not enter becauſe of his <hi>Anger?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 11.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> How ſwift and ſevere was God in this <hi>Cenſure? how unſearchable are his judgements, and his wayes paſt find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>David</hi> was under a very <hi>ſinful paſsion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. <hi>g</hi> 4.</note> when <hi>he would have the people numbred:</hi> all the rational and religious <hi>diſſuaſives</hi> which
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170519:35"/>
                  <hi>Joab</hi> (the then <hi>Generall</hi> of his army) did uſe, could not allay the ſtorm, nor divert him from his ſinful purpoſe. Nothing can ſtand before the flame of his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>The Kings word prevailed againſt Joab,</hi> though that flame conſumed ſeventy thouſand of his Subjects. verſ. 16. Nor was that the onely inſtance of <hi>Davids</hi> diſtempered anger, there was a time when the ſame fire had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured and burnt down <hi>an whole innocent family</hi> to the ground,
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 25.22. <hi>cum</hi> 18.</note> for the unnaturalneſſe of a <hi>Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Maſter,</hi> had not the <hi>wiſdom</hi> of a <hi>prudent Governeſſe</hi> timely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervened.</p>
               <p>The Diſciples of our Lord, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Samaritans; did not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain Chriſt according to their expectations,
<note place="margin">Luke 9.53. Ver. 54.</note> (although the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt ſeems to make ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology for the refuſal; <hi>his face was as if he would go to Jeruſalem</hi>) they break out into <hi>Paſsion,</hi> and <hi>fire preſently muſt be fetcht from heaven to conſume them.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:170519:35"/>
               <p>For which, though they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the <hi>Example of Elijah,</hi> yet <hi>their Lord</hi> obſerved the <hi>diſtemper,</hi> and rebukes it; <hi>Ye know not what manner of ſpirit ye are of:</hi> q. d. Alas, you are miſtaken in the frame of your own hearts; this <hi>impreſsion</hi> is not <hi>zeal</hi> but <hi>anger.</hi> It was another kind of ſpirit which acted <hi>Elijah,</hi> when he call'd for <hi>fire from heaven upon the two Captains and their fifties:</hi> an <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible flame</hi> of juſt zeal firſt fell from heaven upon his <hi>heart,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſatcht thoſe <hi>viſible flames</hi> from heaven upon their <hi>heads.</hi> There was cauſe enough to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie ſo ſevere an execution.</p>
               <p>The wicked King <hi>Abaziah,</hi> which ſent thoſe <hi>Purſevants</hi> for <hi>Elijah,</hi> (with his Grand-father <hi>Saul</hi>) had <hi>forſaken</hi> the <hi>Oracle of God</hi> to <hi>conſult</hi> with the <hi>Devill.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Kings 1.6.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Servants</hi> (of the ſame ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit with their Maſter) come in a <hi>proud imperious way; The King ſaith come down;</hi> with the <hi>Kings mandamus,</hi> they think to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170519:36"/>
                  <hi>heaven</hi> it ſelfe. Yea, while they ſeem to give him his <hi>title, thou man of God,</hi> they do at once <hi>deride</hi> his <hi>function,</hi> and <hi>blaſpheme</hi> his <hi>God.</hi> q. d, <q rend="inline">we will ſee what <hi>a man-God</hi> you are, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your God can deliver you out of our hand,will ye obey the King? or will ye not?</q> 
                  <hi>Come down or we will fetch you down:</hi> &amp; now there is nothing to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the controverſie, but a <hi>ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal teſtimony from God himſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore, to vindicate <hi>Gods glory,</hi> and his <hi>own Commiſsion, Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah</hi> imprecates <hi>fire from heaven,</hi> and God, by this flaming anſwer, bears witneſſe to the <hi>juſt frame of</hi> his ſpirit, in ſo direfull a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge.</p>
               <p>This our Saviour found want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his <hi>diſciples,</hi> and therefore rebuketh their <hi>paſsion,</hi> rather then commendeth their zeale: <hi>Ye know not what ſpirit ye are of.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It were eaſie to multiply in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances: but much work is yet behind. I would ſpeak ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170519:36"/>I ſay, concerning our decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed brother; and there is need of it; for many there be (I have too much cauſe to fear) who, themſelves tranſported with <hi>paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and prejudice,</hi> while they ſtudy <hi>parties</hi> more then <hi>truth,</hi> &amp; <hi>having mens perſons in admiration, becauſe of advantage,</hi> would make others and themſelves believe that there was no other <hi>parallel</hi> to be found between theſe venerable ſervants and Saints of God, and our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed brother, ſave only in their <hi>ſinful infirmities,</hi> and eſpecially that of <hi>paſsion.</hi> It cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, but that as he was (in the general <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a man of <hi>like paſsions</hi> with other men; ſo (in ſpeciall) that that black aduſt humour of <hi>choler,</hi> held the predominacy in his individual Conſtitution, which many times gave a <hi>tincture</hi> to his diſcourſe &amp; action: and which ſtanders-by, more <hi>cenſorious</hi> then <hi>candid,</hi> interpreted to his <hi>unjuſt preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice.</hi> But there is two things I
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170519:37"/>ſhall without bluſhing take the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to ſpeak by way of juſt vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication both to his <hi>perſon,</hi> and the <hi>doctrine</hi> before us. <hi>ſc.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That, bleſſed be God, there is another, and more honourable pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel to be held out to the world between theſe Saints of God,</hi> and our beloved brother.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>That the affection of Anger rightly qualified and managed, is of ſingular uſe in the life and work of a Chriſtian; eſpecially of a Miniſter of the Goſpel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">The Paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel.</note> I ſhall now for the juſt and neceſſary vindication of his <hi>Name,</hi> and <hi>Miniſtry</hi> hold out to the world a <hi>Parallel</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Elias</hi> and our Reverend Brother.</p>
               <p>A Parallel, not of <hi>Equality,</hi> but <hi>Conformity;</hi> not of <hi>Rivalry,</hi> but of <hi>Reality;</hi> to which my conſcience doth ſubſcribe as in the preſence of God; and to which (I am confident) the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences alſo of all <hi>judicious</hi> and <hi>impartial</hi> Chriſtians that knew
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170519:37"/>him, will <hi>bear witneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And why ſhould any man, conceive it a preſumption in me, and a boldneſs (almoſt to <hi>ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge)</hi> to mention a parallel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Elijah,</hi> and this ſervant of Jeſus Chriſt? Conſidering,</p>
               <p n="1">1. They were both but <hi>Men.</hi> The Text ſaies <hi>Elias</hi> was <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>A man of like paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions with us.</hi> It is no in jury to perſons of the higheſt ſanctity, to look upon them as men like our ſelves: ſince the Holy Ghoſt himſelf is here our preſident.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is the <hi>ſame Grace of God</hi> which we eye, &amp; honour in both? One ſtar differs from another in glory, yet it is the ſame light which fills the ſtars, though of different magnitude.</p>
               <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin">Sic parvis componere magna ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebam.</note> Such compariſons do not level them in <hi>full</hi> and <hi>juſt propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> but compareth them in a gradual and Evangelical <hi>Analogy</hi> and <hi>likeneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Eſpecially (above all) in as much as the <hi>Children of God,</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:170519:38"/>even in their ſtate of mortality: are not onely <hi>exhorted to,</hi> but <hi>celebrated for, Conformity</hi> and <hi>likeneſs</hi> to their <hi>Heavenly Father? Be you perfect as your Father which is in Heaven is perfect;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 5. ult. 1 Pet. 1.15.</note> And, <hi>be ye Holy as he that hath called you his Holy;</hi> ther's the exhortation.</p>
               <p>And,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3. ult.</note> 
                  <hi>We all with open face beholding as in a glaſs the glory of the Lord are changed into the ſame image from glory to glory;</hi> ther's their <hi>commendation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Warranted by theſe and the like ſcriptural conſiderations, I addreſs my ſelf to the <hi>Paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Elias</hi> was a man of <hi>Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary ſanctity</hi> and <hi>holineſs: Enoch</hi>-like he <hi>walked with God:</hi> a man of much <hi>acquaintance</hi> and <hi>converſe</hi> in <hi>Heaven,</hi> even while he was on earth.</p>
               <p>Such (in his <hi>degree)</hi> was our Reverend Brother, He was a man of <hi>ſingular piety;</hi> he could ſay with as much ſimplicity, as
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170519:38"/>moſt of his brethren in the fleſh (I believe) <hi>truly our fellowſhip is with the Father and with his Son Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 John 1.3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>I am not afraid on his behalf to appeal to his Adverſaries, as once Chriſt did to his <hi>hearers, (ſetting aſide humane frailties,)
<note place="margin">John 8.46.</note> which of you could convince him of ſin?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am confident he is gone to Heaven with as unſteined an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, as moſt of the ſervants of Chriſt ever did, within our knowledge.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Par. </seg>2</label> 
                  <hi>Elias</hi> was an <hi>eminent Prophet of God,</hi> to whom God did in a ſpecial manner <hi>reveal</hi> and <hi>communicate</hi> his counſels and ſecrets.</p>
               <p>This faithful ſervant of Chriſt, was a <hi>Miniſter of the Goſpel; de Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canis Dei:</hi> a <hi>Miniſter,</hi> I ſay, by <hi>Scriptural ordination;</hi> no <hi>intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or up-ſtart</hi> of the times, who, like the falſe Prophets of old, <hi>run before they are ſent,
<note place="margin">Jer. 23.16</note> and ſpeak a viſion of their own heart, and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170519:39"/>not out of the mouth of the Lord.</hi> This ſervant of God was not ſo, but as his <hi>Call</hi> was from <hi>God,</hi> both <hi>inward</hi> and <hi>outward,</hi> ſo the <hi>ſecret of the Lord was with him;</hi> God was pleaſed to reveal much of himſelf, and of the <hi>myſteries</hi> of the Kingdome of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt unto him; which he did faithfully communicate to the flock, <hi>over which the Holy Ghoſt had made him overſeer;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 20.20.</note> and <hi>kept back nothing that was profitable unto them, but ſhewed them, and taught them publickly, and from houſe to houſe:</hi> a man he was of more then ordinary abilities both of <hi>gifts</hi> and <hi>graces,</hi> for the work of his Miniſterie.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">par. </seg>3</label> 
                  <hi>Elias</hi> was a father and <hi>Chief Governour</hi> of the <hi>Colledge</hi> wherein the children of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet were trained up.
<note place="margin">2 King. 2.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Our dear Brother was, though not a <hi>father,</hi> yet, a <hi>ſon</hi> of the Prophets, though not the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour,</hi> yet, an <hi>Alumnus</hi> in the Scools of the Prophets; where
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170519:39"/>he improved his time and ſtudies to a great maturity; to give him his due, he was an <hi>excellent Scholar,</hi> both in the <hi>Arts</hi> &amp; in the <hi>Tongues,</hi> and generally verſt in other kinds of learning; as thoſe that were intimately ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with him can bear wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. He had a notable faculty in <hi>Poetry,</hi> though his intention and attendance upon the <hi>Queen</hi> of all ſciences and profeſſions, the ſtudy of <hi>Divinity,</hi> allowed him no leaſure to indulge his fancy that way: as thinking it <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centrick</hi> to his heavenly motion. He was ſingularly verſt, as gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, in the <hi>Controverſies</hi> between the <hi>Papiſts &amp; Reformed Churches,</hi> ſo ſpecially in the <hi>Controverſies of the times,</hi> which rendred him very able, quick &amp; potent to <hi>convince gain-ſayers,</hi> who in all their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſes with him,
<note place="margin">Act. 6.10.</note> were not able (as it was ſaid of <hi>Steven)</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt <hi>the wiſdom and the Spirit whereby he ſpake:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites.</note> ſave that their <hi>Maſters</hi> have taught them this
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170519:40"/>piece of their <hi>Myſtery;</hi> that what they cannot <hi>cleer</hi> by <hi>argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Non per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuadebis etiamſi perſuaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris.</note> they will <hi>darken</hi> by <hi>cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour;</hi> that whatſoever the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes</hi> be, they will keep the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion,</hi> and <hi>whoever</hi> have the <hi>bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> yet <hi>they</hi> will cry <hi>victory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the next place, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Par. </seg>4</label> 
                  <hi>Elijah</hi> was a <hi>powerful Prophet;</hi> His very <hi>name</hi> imports it, <hi>Eli-jah;</hi> which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>quaſi</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>My ſtrong God Jehovah,</hi> or the <hi>Lord:</hi> in the 1 <hi>King.</hi> 17.1. it is <hi>Elijahu:</hi> that is, <hi>the Lord, He is my ſtrong God.</hi> God indeed was <hi>ſtrong</hi> in <hi>Elijah;</hi> God mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted and magnified his mighty power in <hi>Elijahs</hi> perſon; mighty in <hi>DEED working Miracles. He called down fire from Heaven,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 King. 1.12 14. 1 King. 17.14.15, 16.</note> once and again; <hi>He multiplieth the widows oil in the cruſe,</hi> and the <hi>meal in the barrel;</hi> as <hi>Elijahs Lord</hi> afterward multiplied the <hi>loaves</hi> and the <hi>fiſhes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He divideth the waters of Jor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan with his Mantle.
<note place="margin">2 King. 2.8.</note> The mighty power of God indeed reſted on him, for even the <hi>fire</hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:170519:40"/>and water, obeyed him.</p>
               <p>He was mighty in <hi>WORD;</hi> mighty Evidence whereof you have, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.39. whereas by one Sermon he brought back many thouſands of the Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Iſraelites to the <hi>acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement</hi> and <hi>worſhip</hi> of the <hi>true God:</hi> a like inſtance of Divine power afterwards was that in the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> in the day of <hi>Pente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſt,</hi> who by one Sermon,
<note place="margin">Act. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted</hi> 3000 <hi>Souls.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Such a monument of Divine power was this holy Prophet <hi>Elijah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hence <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt (after him) inherits his <hi>name;</hi> Our Lord himſelf baptiſeth him with it, (as it were;) <hi>This is Elias which was for to come,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 11.14.</note> the expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of which <hi>riddle</hi> (ſo it was to the Jews, with their very Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies, alſo) you have from the mouth of the Angel,
<note place="margin">Luk. 1.17. verſ. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>He ſhall go before Him, in the Spirit and power of Elias.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That promiſe of God to the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170519:41"/>Jews,
<note place="margin">Matth. 4.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Behold I will ſend you E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lijah the Prophet, before the coming of the great and dreadful day of the Lord,</hi> was not to be <hi>literally</hi> underſtood, as the <hi>Scribes</hi> doted, <hi>Matth.</hi> 17.10. as if <hi>Elias</hi> had been <hi>perſonally</hi> to riſe again from the dead, before the Revelation of the <hi>Meſſiah:</hi> but foretold of <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, that he ſhould ſtand up in the Spirit and power of <hi>Elijah,</hi> as the Harbenger of Jeſus Chriſt; and wherein was this power to be exerted? Mark that, for it is very obſervable, <hi>Luk.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 16.17. verſ. 17.</note> 1.16. <hi>Many of the children of Iſrael ſhall he turn to the Lord their God;</hi> and, <hi>to turn the hearts of the fathers to the children, and the diſobedient to the wiſdom of the juſt;</hi> therein the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> was another <hi>Elias,</hi> for, as <hi>Elias</hi> turned back the Idolatrous Iſraelites to the true worſhip of the Lord their God, ſo did <hi>John the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 3.1.</note> by preaching the <hi>doctrine of repentance,</hi> thereby prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them for the Miniſtry of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170519:41"/>Chriſt; turn many to the Lord, ſo it is applied in the third verſe of that third Chapter of St. <hi>Matthew, This is he that was ſpoken of by Iſaias the Prophet,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt was the Succeſſour of <hi>Elias,</hi> not ſo much in doing miracles, as in his <hi>powerful Preaching;</hi> his Miniſtry was a <hi>powerful Miniſtry;</hi> how did he <hi>thunder</hi> againſt the <hi>Phariſees</hi> &amp; <hi>Sadduces</hi> who came to his <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm?
<note place="margin">Matth 3.7.</note> O generation Vipers who hath warned you to flee from the wrath to come?</hi> &amp;c. A terrible <hi>Exordium,</hi> and the whole Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon is of the ſame ſtrein, <hi>ſtart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> and <hi>convincing,</hi> full of <hi>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour:</hi> I have not time to <hi>read</hi> it, much leſs to run a <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe</hi> upon it.</p>
               <p>This gracious ſervant of the Lord, (whom we have this day followed to the Sepulchre) was <hi>Succeſſour</hi> (as I may ſo ſay) both to <hi>Elias</hi> and <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt; not (as I ſaid) in working <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles;</hi> but in a powerful Miniſtry;
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170519:42"/>He was a <hi>Boanerges;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry was a <hi>thundring Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry;</hi> And I would to God, we had more of them; there is need of them; <hi>Thunder,</hi> they ſay, <hi>purgeth the air;</hi> and if ſo; we have need of more ſuch <hi>ſons of thunder</hi> amongſt us, and not ſuch as will preach <hi>placentia</hi> unto peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſow pillows under their el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bows, and ſing men to hell with <hi>ſweet Lullabies</hi> of <hi>peace, peace,</hi> when there is no peace. Our air is peſtilentially infectious, not onely in the <hi>Phyſicians ſence,</hi> who tell us that the cauſe of the late <hi>mortality</hi> among us (yet not uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally healed, though, <hi>bleſſed be the God that heareth prayers,</hi> wonderfully abated) was the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the air;</hi> but in the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines ſence;</hi> our ſpiritual Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions, who tell us our climate is mortally infected with the Peſts of <hi>Hereſies</hi> and <hi>Blaſphemies;</hi> and with the <hi>putrid</hi> ſtinch of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>poiſonous luſts:</hi> and this is the fatal ſource of all our
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170519:42"/>plagues both in Church &amp; State.</p>
               <p>This our precious brother was deeply ſenſible of; and hence it was that his ſpirit was warmed within him to a more than ordinary <hi>degree</hi> of zeal, in his Miniſtry: that ſo he might be an healer in the land of his nativi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, &amp; in the places where he lived.</p>
               <p>His Miniſtry was a ſtartling an awakning convincing warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing clear, inſtructive, edifying Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry: And it wanted not <hi>ſucceſs</hi> (through grace;) God ſet a <hi>ſeal</hi> to his <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> and he ſaw of the <hi>travel of his ſoul,</hi> in all the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces whither Providence ſent him.</p>
               <p>I hope in this place, there be many living monuments of the power of God, in his Miniſtry. As his preaching bare witneſs to God, ſo God bare witneſs to his preaching, in raiſing up a <hi>ſpiritual ſeed</hi> thereby, to his el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Brother, the Lord Jeſus.</p>
               <p>I am confident there be many here, as in other places, to whom he might ſay,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.2.</note> 
                  <hi>The ſeal of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170519:43"/>my Apoſtleſhip are ye in the Lord:</hi> and that may ſay again of him,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 9.15.</note> 
                  <hi>My Father, my Father;</hi> who drew their firſt ſpiritual breath under his Miniſtry. <hi>Thanks be unto God for his unſpeakable gift.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, <hi>Elias</hi> was <hi>faithful</hi> in ſtanding up for the Lord even when he thought himſelf <hi>alone;</hi> againſt the tide and torrent of the <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> of that generation: which might juſtly wonder to ſee it ſelf turned <hi>Baaliſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the holy Prophet wanted neither zeal nor courage to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear,
<note place="margin">1 King 19.14. <hi>Ingemuit terrarum orbis ſe Arrianum inveniſſe.</hi> As it was in <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius</hi> his time. 1 Kings 8.22.</note> and proteſt againſt them and their Idolatry to their very faces; I ſay, <hi>alone; The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of Baal are four hundred and fifty men,</hi> but I, even <hi>I ALONE, am a Prophet of the Lord; let them therefore give us two bullocks,</hi> &amp;c. His zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ſpirit could not bear <hi>their halting between two opinions,</hi> and therefore <hi>provokes</hi> them to the <hi>diſpute,</hi> before all the people; the God <hi>that anſweareth by fire, let him be God.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:170519:43"/>
               <p>And his <hi>courage</hi> was rival with his <hi>fidelity,</hi> and zeal.
<note place="margin">verſ. 21.</note> He feared not the face of <hi>Ahab,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">verſ. 24.</note> though a <hi>potent, and a cruel</hi> King; He ſpares not to tell him;
<note place="margin">verſ. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>I have not troubled Iſrael, but thou and thy fathers houſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He feared not all the falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of <hi>Jezabel;</hi> though they had the people to back them; <hi>Take the prophets of Baal,
<note place="margin">verſ. 40.</note> let not one of them eſcape.</hi> What a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſpirit of God was that upon him, that he a <hi>ſingle unarmed man,</hi> ſhould not be afraid to <hi>command</hi> and <hi>ſee</hi> execution to be done, upon four hundred and fifty Idolatrous prophets, under the wing of an Idolatrous Queen, and before the very face of a wicked King? Thouſands of their ſubjects ſtanding by, who but now, were ſo cow'd with fear, that they had not a word to ſay for the <hi>true</hi> and <hi>living God!</hi> here was courage to a Miracle!</p>
               <p>Our reverend brother had his <hi>proportion</hi> of this <hi>fidelity, zeal,</hi>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:170519:44"/>and <hi>courage.</hi> He was <hi>faithful</hi> to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> his <hi>truths</hi> and <hi>ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances.</hi> In all the <hi>Changes</hi> that went over his head, in all the <hi>Controverſies</hi> of the times, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he exerciſed his Miniſtery, he he was a moſt ſtrenuous Aſſertor of the truth, and amoſt coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious oppoſer of <hi>Error</hi> and <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation;</hi> and that even while ſome higher then other by head ſhoulders, (in their own eyes) did baſely and unworthily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray their Cauſe. Hee fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not the face of man, in the Cauſe of Jeſus Chriſt. He durſt tell the greateſt perſon he had to do with of their faults,
<note place="margin">Malleus <hi>haeretice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi> Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts and Antinomi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ans, Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſts, &amp;c.</note> upon juſt occaſion, in the worſt of times. He was an <hi>hammer</hi> to beat down error and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, where ever it met him; he could not bear with them that preach down <hi>Poedo-baptiſme;</hi> the <hi>Chriſtian Sabbath, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities, Schooles of Learning;</hi> ordination, and other ordinances and inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of Jeſus Chriſt. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170519:44"/>propheſieth to us of ſome, and in the latter times, that <hi>will not endure ſound doctrine;</hi> it was the zeal and fidelity of our bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that he could not endure <hi>unſound doctrine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.3.</note> no not the <hi>liſpings,</hi> or likeneſſe of it, knowing the dangerous <hi>tendency</hi> thereof.</p>
               <p>Falſe opinions do inſinuate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by the uſe of dark &amp; dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous expreſſions; and it is the poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of ſeducers and men of corrupt principles, when they dare not ſpeak out to ſhun the <hi>form of plain and wholeſome words,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 2 Tim, 1.13. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Plaiſtred coyned words.</hi> 2 Pet. 2.3. Rev. 2.2.</note> and hide themſelves under the masks of ſuſpitious and doubtfull phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; or <hi>feigned words,</hi> as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> calls them; and ſo by new lights, and new language, they do inſenſibly undermine the truth, and introduce their looſe and rotten opinions.</p>
               <p>This he could not bear with ſeducers, nor they with him; ſo that by this means he became <hi>a man of contention,
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.8.</note> his righteous
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170519:45"/>ſoul was vexed from day to day, in ſeeing and hearing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixthly, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Paral. </seg>6</label> 
                  <hi>Elias</hi> was a man of a very <hi>tender ſpirit:</hi> tender of the glory of God. <hi>I have been very jealous for the Lord of Hoſts.</hi> Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of his Saints and ſervants, and ordinances; ſo he continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his complaint. <hi>The children of Iſrael have forſaken thy Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,
<note place="margin">1 King. 19.10.14.</note> deſtroyed thine altars, and ſlain thy Prophets with the ſword:</hi> his ſoul bled within him, over the precious <hi>things</hi> and <hi>ſervants</hi> of God; though he had his own life for a prey, <hi>I onely am left;</hi> this could not ſatisfie his zealous ſpirit.</p>
               <p>Our honoured Friend (now with God) was a man (in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree) of ſuch another ſpirit: He was <hi>jealous for God,</hi> and for the intereſts of Jeſus Chriſt: they lay upon his heart with a great weight, and made deep bleeding impreſſions: His word was oft with <hi>Joſhua, And what wilt thou for thy great name?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joſh. 7.9,</note>
               </p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:170519:45"/>
               <p>Very tender towards <hi>the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God,</hi> his bowels wrought and melted within him towards poor periſhing ſouls.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chattam</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi>
                  </note> The Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of this place, are his wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, before God and man; For your ſakes, that fear God here</p>
               <p>What <hi>offers</hi> hath he <hi>refuſed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What <hi>affronts</hi> hath he <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuſteined?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What <hi>temptations</hi> hath he <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What <hi>oppoſition</hi> and reproach hath he <hi>born?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With what <hi>difficulties</hi> and <hi>ſtraits</hi> hath he <hi>conflicted,</hi> for many yeares together,
<note place="margin">Phil. 2.30.</note> not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding his own life, or the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments of a numerous and neceſſitous family, to ſupply your ſpiritual neceſſities; He <hi>did ſpend</hi> and <hi>was ſpent,</hi> he even offer'd up <hi>himſelf upon the ſacrifice, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of your faith:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſe 17.</note> truly he was not only your <hi>Miniſter;</hi> but even a <hi>Martyr,</hi> among you.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:170519:46"/>
               <p>What love, and honour, and mercy, and liberality, you owe unto his <hi>Name,</hi> and <hi>poor Orphan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>familie,</hi> left with you, judge ye? Surely if he ſowed unto you <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual things,</hi> it is no great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter if his poor family <hi>reap your carnal things,</hi> through his pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty you were made rich; in the midſt of your riches let not his <hi>Relicts</hi> remaine poor. But to proceed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Elias,</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Paral. </seg>7</label> was a <hi>mortified man.</hi> He was ſo far from living to the world, that he hardly lived <hi>in</hi> the world: like his ſucceſſor and anty-type, <hi>John the Baptiſt</hi> he lived <hi>ſeparated from</hi> the world while he was in it,
<note place="margin">Matth. 3.4.</note> chooſing ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to live among <hi>bruit beaſts,</hi> then among <hi>bruitiſh men;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 King. 1.8.</note> his <hi>fare</hi> hard, and his <hi>raiment</hi> courſe, both ſuitable to a wilderneſſe, not to Court or City.</p>
               <p>This <hi>man of God,</hi> now <hi>with</hi> God, was a man dead to the world, while he lived in it. He was not a man of the <hi>mode,</hi> his
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170519:46"/>habit and diet ſpake a mortified frame of heart. He was not given to juncating, and feaſting, and ranting, with vain and wanton perſons, as the manner of ſome is, to the infinite ſcandal of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>He ſought not <hi>great things for himſelf,</hi> nor laid about him to fether his neſt, as ſome do that would be counted Saints of the firſt, magnitude. (Veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly covetouſneſſe never ſo inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the profeſſing party, as in this hypocritical generation wherein we live;) no, our bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was <hi>crucified to the world,
<note place="margin">Gal. 6 14. 2 Cor. 4.18.</note> and the world to him; He lookt not upon the things that are ſeen, but upon the things that are not ſeen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He <hi>coveted no mans ſilver or gold,</hi> never any man paſſed under harder <hi>preſſures,</hi> with greater ſilence and contendedneſſe: He had but little, yet when deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded how it was with him? he would alwayes reply (with much
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170519:47"/>cheerfulneſſe, <hi>he had enough,</hi> and <hi>wanted nothing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea, in the midſt of all his <hi>ſtraits,</hi> he was not only <hi>unqueru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous,</hi> but <hi>liberal,</hi> liberal even to <hi>profuſeneſſe:</hi> He never cared <hi>how little was given him,</hi> nor <hi>how much he gave to others,</hi> that were due objects of charity: Covetous he was, only in <hi>laying out for Chriſt,</hi> not in <hi>laying up for himſelf:</hi> and ſurely his compaſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate ſpirit had undone him long ſince, had not that promiſe recrui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him.
<note place="margin">Iſa 32.8.</note> 
                  <hi>The liberal man deviſeth liberal things, and by liberal things he ſhall ſtand:</hi> and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.26. <hi>he is ever mercifull, and lendeth, and his ſeed is bleſſed.</hi> The Lord make good this his promiſe to this ſurviving <hi>Orphans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the next place, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Paral. </seg>8</label> 
                  <hi>Elijah</hi> was a man <hi>much</hi> and <hi>mighty in prayer:</hi> the Text repreſents ſo much un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, <hi>Elijah</hi> was a man ſubject to like paſſions as we are, yet <hi>he prayed earneſtly,</hi> &amp;c. &amp; (in another place) the Scripture calls him the <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor</hi>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:170519:47"/>of <hi>Iſrael. Wote ye not how</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lijah <hi>mirketh interceſſion to God for</hi> Iſrael:
<note place="margin">Rom. 11 2.</note> Elijah by his prayers was <hi>a Mediator</hi> between God and his people.</p>
               <p>And ſurely our Brother was <hi>a man of prayer,</hi> much in prayer, both <hi>with</hi> the people of God, and <hi>for</hi> them: in <hi>publick,</hi> in <hi>private,</hi> in <hi>their houſes,</hi> and in his <hi>own houſe</hi> and cloſet, he poured out his ſoul to God night and day. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>England</hi> hath loſt one of her Interceſſors, one of the Lords re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancers, a <hi>Moſes,</hi> a <hi>Samuel,</hi> a <hi>Jacob,</hi> a wreſtler with God, who ſtood in the gap, and helped to turn away the wrath of God from a ſinfull nation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Elijah</hi> was much in <hi>faſting,</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Paral. </seg>9</label> as well as in prayer,
<note place="margin">1 King. 19.8.</note> 
                  <hi>he faſted forty dayes and forty nights,</hi> at one time. This holy man was frequent in this duty, he joyned <hi>faſting</hi> with prayer not ſeldom; ſo that he might well, with the Apoſtle, put it into his Catalogue,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.27.</note> I cannot call it, the <hi>Catalogue</hi> of <hi>ſufferings,</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:170519:48"/>becauſe he counted ſuch dayes as his <hi>feaſting dayes, in faſtings of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</hi> It was <hi>his meat and drink,</hi> thus <hi>to do the will of his heavenly Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Elias</hi> was a <hi>perſecuted Prophet,</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Paral. </seg>10</label> one of thoſe our Saviour menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<note place="margin">Mar. 5.12. 1 Kings 10.18. Ch. 19.1, 2, 3.</note> in his <hi>Beatitudes: ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted they the Prophets that were before you:</hi> perſecuted by <hi>Ahab,</hi> and perſecuted by <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabel,</hi> put to <hi>flye for his life;</hi> and often driven by the ſeverer diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations of providence from place to place: he was one of thoſe holy <hi>wanderers,</hi> the Holy Ghoſt makes mention of <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.37. <hi>they wandred about in Sheep-skins, and Goat-skins, being deſtitute, afflicted, tormented.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This faithful Miniſter of the Goſpel he had his ſhare in the <hi>perſecution</hi> of the times wherein he lived, from his very firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance upon his Miniſtry: accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the propheſie of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.11, 12. and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it had been a wonder if he
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170519:48"/>ſhould have eſcaped it; For as our Lord ſubjoyns the <hi>reaſon</hi> to his prediction of the Apoſtles ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, verſe 13. His Miniſtry was <hi>ſalt,</hi> he was <hi>ſalt</hi> in his <hi>life,</hi> and <hi>ſalt</hi> in his <hi>doctrine;</hi> not only ſavoury, but <hi>quick</hi> and <hi>corroding,</hi> ſmart and ſearching, which cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt times and ulcered conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>could not bear,</hi> 2 Tim. 4.3.</p>
               <p>This enraged and enflamed the ſpirits of unſound men; and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed much trouble and perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt him, whereſoever he came; which gave him occaſion often to <hi>flit</hi> from one place to another, to avoyd the fury of unreaſonable men:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 56.8.</note> And this <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> put among his ſufferings: <hi>Thou telleſt my wandrings, put thou my tears into thy bottle:</hi> And o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the faithfull Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, have had their ſhare with him in this kind of perſecution. <hi>Math.</hi> 10.23. The world cannot beare the plain dealing of Goſpell-Miniſters: there is none ſo <hi>hated</hi> as the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170519:49"/>
                  <hi>Reprover in the gate.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Amos 5.10.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Elias</hi> was <hi>miraculouſly fed and preſerved</hi> in the midſt of all thoſe hardſhips and perſecutions by <hi>immediate Providence.</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Paral. </seg>11</label> A <hi>widow</hi> ready to <hi>periſh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 King. 17.5, 6. Verſe 9.12, 15, 17.</note> is his <hi>Suckler,</hi> and a <hi>bird of prey,</hi> his <hi>Caterer,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The <hi>providences of God</hi> toward our <hi>Reverend Brother,</hi> were <hi>highly obſervable;</hi> ſurely in the eyes of many ſtanders by, it was little leſſe then a miracle, how he and his numerous family have ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, for divers years laſt elap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; his <hi>viſible revenue</hi> not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving exceeded 30 l. <hi>per annum.</hi> But he lived by <hi>Faith,</hi> and not by <hi>Senſe;</hi> that promiſe was his beſt <hi>ſalary,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.3.</note> Truſt in the Lord, and do good, and verily thou ſhalt be fed.</hi> He was not a man that would take Gods work out of his hand, and neglect his own, as many do; he look't to the <hi>condition,</hi> and truſted <hi>God</hi> to make good the <hi>promiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Elias <hi>appeared with Chriſt in the Mount of transfiguration.</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Paral. </seg>12</label>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 17 3.</note>
               </p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:170519:49"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>This ſervant of Chriſt</hi> had his <hi>tranfigurations</hi> alſo,
<note place="margin">Though he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with <hi>Bern. Rara hara, bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis mora.</hi> 1 Pet. 1.8.</note> Jeſus Chriſt did ſometimes call him up into the mountain, where he ſhewed him his <hi>glory;</hi> he had in his propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion his <hi>viſions,</hi> and <hi>revelations</hi> ſometimes full of <hi>joy unſpeakable and glorious.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Elijah</hi> when he was to leave the world,
<note place="margin">2 King. 2.8.</note> his way lay through <hi>Jordan,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 130.1.</note> and our Brother had his <hi>Jordan</hi> alſo, to paſſe through, <hi>deep waters</hi> of <hi>deſertion,</hi> which threatned to go over his ſoul, and out <hi>of theſe depths he cried to the Lord.</hi> But it was his <hi>happineſſe</hi> and <hi>honour</hi> that he found <hi>Elijah</hi>'s <hi>mantle</hi> as well as his <hi>Jordane,</hi> his <hi>faith</hi> I mean. For ſurely, it was the <hi>faith</hi> of <hi>Elijah</hi> that divided <hi>Jordan,</hi> and not his <hi>garment.</hi> And by the vertue of this faith, did this <hi>precious man</hi> go through his <hi>Jordan,</hi> ſo that the waters did not <hi>drown him; God hid his face from him</hi> for a ſeaſon, <hi>and he was troubled:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 30.7.</note> But he was pleaſed to diſpell the cloud, and <hi>cauſed his
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170519:50"/>face to ſhine upon him again:</hi> which cauſed his departing ſoule to break forth into this trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a little before his <hi>laſt breath. VICTORY, VI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CTORY, VICTORY.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Devil was a Coward, and durſt not ſet upon this holy man, till he thought <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> and (almoſt) <hi>Sence</hi> were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted, and could make no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſtance. But the Lord Jeſus <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving loved this his Diſciple, loved him to the end:</hi> and was ſtrong in his weak ſervant to overcome the <hi>Devil,</hi> in this laſt encounter, ſo that he breathed out his ſoul and his <hi>doxologie</hi> together, <hi>THANKS BE TO GOD FOR JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And yet let us follow <hi>Elias</hi> a ſtep or two further with <hi>Eliſhah</hi> his ſervant: <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Paral. </seg>14</label>
                  <note place="margin">2 Reg. 1.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Elias went up to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in a fiery Chariot:</hi> our Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was carried up in <hi>a burning fever,</hi> or rather he aſcended up into glory in the triumphant Chariot of <hi>victorious aſſurance</hi>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:170519:50"/>of the love of God in Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.37.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Paral. </seg>15</label> 
                  <hi>Elijah let fall his mantle up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his ſervant Eliſhah,</hi> who followed him in his <hi>aſcenſion,</hi> both with his <hi>eye</hi> and <hi>voyce. My Father, my Father,
<note place="margin">2 Rings 2.12.</note> the Chariot of Iſrael, and the horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men thereof.</hi> This <hi>good man</hi> let fall the mantle of <hi>bleſſings and prayers,</hi> upon his dear <hi>Friends</hi> and <hi>Relations;</hi> that ſtood crying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him, in ſome ſuch kind of phraſe. My Father, my Father, &amp;c. a bleſſing ſuitable to the ſtate &amp; condition of every <hi>ſtander-ly:</hi> And thus this ſervant of Chriſt made his <hi>LAST Will</hi> and <hi>Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> &amp; (if I be not miſtaken) his <hi>ONLY Will</hi> &amp; <hi>Teſtament</hi> of <hi>Praiſe and Prayer, praiſing God,</hi> and <hi>bleſſing men.</hi> And thus much for the <hi>Parallel</hi> between <hi>Elijah</hi> and our Reverend Brother.</p>
               <p>I come now to the ſecond thing, propounded for the juſt vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our <hi>Brother,</hi> &amp; of the <hi>truth</hi> it ſelf, and that is to ſhew you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the affection of Anger
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170519:51"/>rightly qualified, and managed, is of ſingular uſe and advantage in the life and work of a Chriſtian, eſpecially of a Miniſter of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,</hi> which ought in no wiſe to be branded with the uſual ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal of <hi>choler</hi> and <hi>paſsion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I make no queſtion, the falſe prophets, and their ſeduced pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelytes, ſtuck not to blaſt the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Prophet in my Text, with the ſame reproach, <hi>a furious man,</hi> a man of an <hi>intemperate</hi> and <hi>unbridled ſpirit,</hi> that valued not mens lives, but in his anger would not ſtick to call down fire from Heaven to deſtroy an <hi>hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred men at a time,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The very <hi>meek Spirit of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords</hi> it here, in my Text; that he was <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>of like paſſions with us;</hi> and yet without any diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to his <hi>memorial</hi> in the land of the living.</p>
               <p>To which end let me, 1. in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, put you in mind of this, <hi>viz. That the paſſion of anger,</hi> with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther affections in nature, at what
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170519:51"/>time the perſon in whom they are is <hi>regenerate;</hi> they do <hi>change</hi> their nature, and become <hi>rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate too:</hi> and being baptized with the <hi>blood</hi> and <hi>ſpirit</hi> of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, they receive <hi>Divine impreſſions,</hi> and ſo paſs into the catalogue of <hi>gracious affections and diſpoſitions,</hi> and become in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of exceeding honour and ſervice in the hand of Jeſus Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Jam. 3.17.</note> who is pleaſed to make uſe of them in his own work: ex gr.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>WIT,</hi> regenerate, becometh <hi>Heavenly wiſdom.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>LOVE,</hi> ſanctified,
<note place="margin">Gal. 5.6. Faith working by Love.</note> becomes <hi>an active principle in the hand of Faith.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>FEAR,</hi> beſprinkled with the blood of Chriſt, becomes a notable <hi>Andidote and prefervative againſt ſin.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Hate I not them that hate thee, &amp;c. Pſal. 139.21.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>HATRED,</hi> ſpiritualized, an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Antipaethy</hi> with any <hi>thing</hi> or <hi>perſon</hi> contrary to God.</item>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:170519:52"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RAGE,</hi> ſanctified by the Holy Ghoſt,
<note place="margin">Zach. He that is as David ſhall be like an Angel of God.</note> is turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a kind of <hi>Angelical for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude.</hi> And thus to be ſhort.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>PASSION,</hi> born again of water and the ſpirit, becometh the grace of <hi>Zeal;</hi> and holy <hi>jealouſy</hi> for God, and for the intereſt of Jeſus Chriſt.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anger</hi> ſanctified is that to the affections, which <hi>edge</hi> is to the <hi>inſtrument,</hi> which <hi>varniſh</hi> is to colours, which <hi>wind</hi> is to the <hi>ſails</hi> of a ſhip; <hi>judgment</hi> is the <hi>ballaſt,</hi> but zeal is the full <hi>gale,</hi> it is as <hi>mettle to the horſe;</hi> it is the <hi>activity</hi> of every grace; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very affection <hi>red hot</hi> for Jeſus Chriſt;
<note place="margin">Cant. 8.7.</note> 
                  <hi>which much water can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not quench, neither can the floods drown it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In a word <hi>paſſion refined</hi> and <hi>ſpiritualized,</hi> is every faculty of the Soul, acting <hi>to its height,</hi> for the glory of God: <hi>The zeal
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170519:52"/>of thy houſe hath eaten me up.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 69 9.</note> To be ſhort; <hi>Sanctified anger</hi> in the Saints of God is not that which the world takes it to be; a <hi>ſhort madneſs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 31. <hi>Furor ira brevis.</hi>
                  </note> but a <hi>grace</hi> of the Spirit of God; yea, it is a <hi>compound</hi> and <hi>temperament</hi> of all graces, acting in <hi>ſummo gradu</hi> in the height of intention, for the promoting of the concernments of Chriſts Kingdom.</p>
               <p>I told before, that <hi>Elijah</hi> was an uſeful man, <hi>though</hi> he was <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to paſſion;</hi> I ſhall tell you more now; He was <hi>therefore ſo uſeful, BECA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE he was ſubject to paſſion;</hi> his anger and paſſion being ſanctified, <hi>made</hi> him ſo abundantly active for God and the reformation of the <hi>publick worſhip, doctrine,</hi> and <hi>ordinances,</hi> in his generation; had he wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his <hi>paſsion,</hi> he had wanted ſome of his <hi>zeal,</hi> for God.</p>
               <p>And ſo it was with our wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy brother deceaſed. That which an idle wanton, looſe luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warm generation, of <hi>profeſſors,</hi> as
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170519:53"/>well as <hi>prophane</hi> perſons (for the palliating of their own hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie and <hi>Gallio-like</hi>-indifferency in matters of religion) called <hi>paſſion</hi> and <hi>choler</hi> in him, was in deed and in truth nothing but his <hi>zeal,</hi> and <hi>courage</hi> and <hi>activity</hi> for Jeſus Chriſt, which truly did even <hi>conſume him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alas! in this apoſtate genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, all things have loſt their proper names; the <hi>Devil</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in <hi>Samuels mantle. Satan</hi> in the form of an <hi>Angel of light:</hi> and <hi>ſin</hi> puts on the habit of <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue:</hi> that it may deceive the more ſafely.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Luke-warmneſs</hi> and curſed <hi>neutrality</hi> in religion, paſſeth abroad for <hi>meekneſs</hi> and <hi>ſweetneſs of Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Carnal Policy</hi> for Chriſtian <hi>Prudence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Curſed Compliance</hi> with the luſts of men for <hi>moderation</hi> and command of a mans ſpirit, <hi>&amp; ſic in coeteris.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>While <hi>zeal</hi> and <hi>fidelity,</hi> to the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170519:53"/>truth, ordinances and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Jeſus Chriſt heare ill, in the world; and ſuffer all the odium and ſcandal that a revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling world, and the venemous wit of malice can heap upon it. Truly, <hi>the earth is not able to bear their words.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore,
<note place="margin">Jam. 2.14. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> you that fear God, <hi>be inſtructed,</hi> and take heed, how ye <hi>became Judges of evil thoughts;</hi> that ye do not judge perverſly, according to your own <hi>corrupt thoughts,</hi> or accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the corrupt <hi>thoughts</hi> of the men of the world, whoſe judgment is totally perverted by carnal intereſt, and vile af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. Take heed,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 5.</note> ye do not <hi>call good evil and evil good, put light for daokneſs and darkneſs for light;</hi> and ſo condemn the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of Gods Children, <hi>and bleſs the proud whom the Lord ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horreth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus having premiſed thus much in general, concerning <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> and <hi>paſſion</hi> in the Saints;</p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:170519:54"/>
               <p>Becauſe indeed, even where this affection is ſanctified, it is not ſanctified quite through; but may have even in the beſt of Saints, and without queſtion in this ſervant of Chriſt, <hi>had</hi> ſome mixtures of the old corrupt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, troubling and diſtempering it ſometimes, which makes the Saints go mourning and ſighing within themſelves, and wiſhing to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt; Let me come now in the <hi>ſecond place.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To a more diſtinct and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular reſolution of the queſtion;</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>When, and in what Caſes, Anger and paſsion in the Saints is to be adjudged as ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied zeal, a pure flame of divine love?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> For Reſolution of this query, I ſhall give you four or five <hi>Notes</hi> or <hi>Rules,</hi> (and very briefly) for to guide your judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in this particular.</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:170519:54"/>
               <p>Firſt, I muſt tell you,
<note place="margin">Firſt Rule</note> 
                  <hi>thus</hi> much, that <hi>every warm and keen expreſsion, whether by way of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof or Caution, is not to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted anger and paſsion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A man may ſpeak <hi>earneſtly</hi> and <hi>vehemently</hi> in the calmeſt temper of his ſpirit: ſome mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter requires a greater Emphaſis to ſet it on then other: it is the skill and wiſdom of an Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, to <hi>edge</hi> and <hi>accent</hi> his diſcourſe with a due pondus. He ſhould be but a dull ſpeaker, that ſhould deliver matter of weight in the ſame key, and tone as if he were but dictating to his Scholars, or reading a le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture. And yet this is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon miſtake of the injudicious multitude, to interpret every im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuous and pathetical poſture of the preacher (eſpecially when the matter lieth croſs to corrupt nature) for <hi>anger</hi> and <hi>intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rancy</hi> of ſpirit. Obſerve it, and you will find that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> expreſs a great deal of rancor
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170519:55"/>and venom in a <hi>ſlie</hi> and <hi>calm phraſe;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Meekneſs &amp; paſſion may dwell in the ſame, though a man may be paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal &amp; yet of a meek ſpirit. So was <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</hi>
                  </note> ſo on the other ſide ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity may be accompanied, with much <hi>meekneſs</hi> and <hi>love</hi> in a <hi>keener</hi> and <hi>ſharper ſtile.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, ſecondly; When the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemency of a mans ſpirit <hi>is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted againſt ſin,</hi> then it is not to be accompted <hi>paſsion</hi> ſo much as <hi>zeal.</hi> It is the Apoſtles rule.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Be ye angry and ſin not;</hi> q. d. If ye would not <hi>ſin in your anger;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Second Rule. Eph. 4 26.</note> be angry onely <hi>againſt ſin.</hi> It is <hi>ſin</hi> which teacheth men to call it anger, when <hi>it ſelf</hi> is reproved; for this is the deceit; do but call the reproof <hi>paſsion</hi> and <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice,</hi> and then men think they need not regard it: the <hi>guilt</hi> is tranſlated upon the <hi>reprover,</hi> and the <hi>delinquent</hi> is <hi>juſtified.</hi> What judgement would the <hi>tame ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits</hi> of our times have paſſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that act of <hi>Phineas,</hi> in that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere execution done, upon thoſe impudent adulterers,
<note place="margin">Nemb. 25.7, 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Zimri</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in that ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration? How would they have
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170519:55"/>ſentenced it to the pit of hell, as an act of <hi>furious cruelty.</hi> What? to execute <hi>before trial!</hi> To make himſelf, both <hi>witneſs, judge</hi> &amp; <hi>exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioner?</hi> An that in the very act of <hi>ſin?</hi> thereby cutting them off from the hope or poſſibility of repentance, (in humane proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility) he deſtroyed both body and Soul at once, <hi>paſsion</hi> above all <hi>hyperbolie!</hi> I, but the <hi>Searcher of hearts, the Righteous Judge of Heaven and earth;</hi> He calleth it <hi>zeal:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Numb. 25.11, 12, 13.</note> an act of <hi>juſtice</hi> whereby <hi>Phineas</hi> prevented the execution of <hi>divine juſtice,</hi> upon the whole <hi>Congregation;</hi> and for a <hi>reward</hi> whereof, God entails upon <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neis</hi> and his ſeed the <hi>Covenant of an everlaſting Prieſthood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, When <hi>anger is ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened againſt errour and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy;</hi> it is not to be reputed <hi>cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> and <hi>paſsion!</hi> Brethren, what think ye, can a man indeed be guilty of <hi>paſsion</hi> againſt the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid <hi>opinions</hi> and <hi>hereſies</hi> which <hi>ſubvert the very foundation?</hi>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:170519:56"/>or can there be an <hi>Exceſſe</hi> in that paſſion? can a man be bitter againſt <hi>drunkenneſſe</hi> and <hi>whoredome?</hi> or can a man be guilty of railing againſt <hi>damnable Doctrines, Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiſme,
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.1.</note> Arianiſme, (denying the Lord that
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Bought them</hi> in ſenſu Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtico, <hi>or bought</hi> them, <hi>in their own perſwaſion.</hi>
                     </note> bought them) Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripturiſme, Quakeriſme, Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſme?</hi> what not.</p>
               <p>Did ye never read the Epiſtles of Saint <hi>Paul:</hi> Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> Saint <hi>Jude?</hi> oh how do they ſharpen their <hi>ſtyle</hi> againſt falſe Teachers, and ſeducers, branding them, wih the higheſt ignominies that can drop from an inſpired pen, <q>Dogges,
<note place="margin">Phil. 3.2.</note> Wolves, Evill-work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Wells without water; Clouds carried about with a tempeſt,
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2. <hi>per tot.</hi> Jude <hi>per tot.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Full of the whore.</hi>
                     </note> to whom is reſerved the myſt of darkneſſe for ever, preſumptuous railers, bruit beaſts; having eyes full of adultery; covetous, curſed children, raging waves, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring ſtarres, to whom is reſerved the blackneſſe of darkneſſe for ever. <hi>Cains
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170519:56"/>Balaams, Cores</hi> filthy dream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, murmurers, Complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, ſenſual Separatiſts, who pretend to the ſpirit, but have it not.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe and many like, are the <hi>Marks</hi> which the meek ſpirit of God ſets upon theſe <hi>Cains:</hi> which if a Miniſter of the Goſpel ſhould but ſo much as repeat, in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the diſſeminators of the very ſelf-ſame curſed principles &amp; practiſes in our times they ſhould be reviled, &amp; well nigh Curſt, and ſtoned to death, as men of bitter &amp; virulent ſpirits; the multitude of Sectaries, would <hi>tear off their clothes, and caſt duſt into the aire; and lift up their voices; and cry out</hi> as the enraged Jewes againſt <hi>Panl.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Away with ſuch a fellow,
<note place="margin">Acts 22.22, 23. 1 Cor. 4.3.</note> it is not fit he ſhould live.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But brethren, it is <hi>a ſmall thing for us to be judged by mans judgement.</hi> The <hi>Meek Apoſtle,</hi> by the <hi>meek Spirit</hi> of God,
<note place="margin">Tit. 1 13. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> hath commanded us, <hi>to rebuke them
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170519:57"/>ſharply, cuttingly;</hi> a metaphor bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from <hi>Chirurgions</hi> who cut, and ſearch, and lance, and apply corraſives,
<note place="margin">Ne pars ſinceratra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hatur.</note> that they may eat out the dead and putrified fleſh, that the whole body may not periſh. This is not to <hi>kill,</hi> but to <hi>ſave,</hi> not to <hi>wound,</hi> but to <hi>Cure;</hi> that <hi>they may be ſound in the faith.</hi> The meekneſſe, the love, the mercy, the gentleneſſe lieth in the <hi>tendency</hi> of ſuch bitter <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſives.</hi> In this caſe <hi>tenderneſſe</hi> in the Mediums would be <hi>cruelty</hi> in the <hi>End,
<note place="margin">Levit. 19.17. <hi>Fourth Rule.</hi>
                     </note> hatred,</hi> and not love.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Anger is no longer <hi>Anger,</hi> but <hi>zeal,</hi> when it is <hi>in the cauſe of God,</hi> &amp; for his glory: this <hi>rule</hi> differs not from the former in <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> but in <hi>notion</hi> only, as ſomewhat more general.
<note place="margin">Gal. 4.18. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>It is good to be zealouſly affected in a good thing always:</hi> the word ſignifies to be <hi>red hot,</hi> to be <hi>boyling over;</hi> this is a temper becoming the ſervants, &amp; the work of a <hi>jealous</hi> God. It is good when every paſſion is made to ſerve the intereſt of Chriſt. We
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170519:57"/>ſhould be cold in our <hi>own Cauſe,</hi> but hot in <hi>Gods.</hi> Zeal in our own concerns, is paſſion, paſſion in Gods affaires is zeal; The temper of meek <hi>Moſes;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Num. 12.1.</note> who was ſilent in his own reproach, though by a <hi>Brother and a Siſter,</hi> (and therefore leſſe portable. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.12.) or if he ſpake, it was in <hi>prayer</hi> for them, verſe 13. not in <hi>paſſion</hi> againſt them.</p>
               <p>And this was the temper of our dear brother. I dare ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal even to his <hi>Adverſaries,</hi> was not his anger againſt ſin, Againſt errour and falſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, of which he met with too much, in every place? Was it not (whether in publick or private) in the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of God, and of <hi>Religion,</hi> the concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Jeſus Chriſt, and of mens immortal ſoules?</p>
               <p>Indignities and affronts offered to himſelf, did not tempt out the fervour and acrimony of his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, as thoſe which were put upon Chriſt and his precious Truths.</p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:170519:58"/>
               <p>If ſo, &amp; your conſciences cannot gainſay it, call him no more, an <hi>angry, paſsionate, cholsrick</hi> man; but call him a <hi>faithful, plain-deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, zealous</hi> Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt: leſt otherwiſe God hear and be angry, and judge you for your paſſion and partialty.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Rule. </seg>5</label> 
                  <hi>When the warmth and keenneſſe of a mans ſpirit is acted not ſo much againſt the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> as againſt the <hi>wickedneſs</hi> of men, who hold the truth of God in unrighteouſneſſe. <hi>Call it not anger and paſsion, bat zeal for God,</hi> and <hi>compaſsion on mens ſouls. Paſsion</hi> lets flye its arrows againſt the <hi>perſons of men,</hi> zeal only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their <hi>ſins:</hi> Indeed ſins and perſons are ſo near, that a man can hardly diſtinguiſh ſometimes between the <hi>perſon</hi> and the <hi>ſin.</hi> to avoyd the danger therefore, let men ſtand furtther off from their ſins, that he that ſtrikes at their ſins, may not with the ſame blow be judged to ſtrike at their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons alſo. But this is that which
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170519:58"/>I ſay, the heat of anger muſt be againſt the <hi>crime,</hi> rather then againſt the <hi>perſon;</hi> and when it is mixt with <hi>grief,</hi> which ſets <hi>pity</hi> and <hi>prayer</hi> on work for the offending party, as it is ſaid of Chriſt, <hi>Mark</hi> 3.5. then it is pure zeal, and not diſtemper'd <hi>anger.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have done both with the <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> and with the <hi>occaſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Onely in as much as the Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Regenerate (as I hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before) are not all over rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate; nor have I made this A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology for the Saints in general, or <hi>this our brother</hi> (for whoſe loſs we mourn this day) in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, as if I conceived there were no ſin in their Anger, no <hi>ſtrange fire</hi> in their paſſion, yea, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Saints of God, <hi>diſcover</hi> much <hi>diſtemper</hi> in their affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and paſſions ſometimes, even when they act for God, (for which they judge themſelves bitterly in the preſence of God;) for the preventing of miſtakes on the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170519:59"/>right hand, or on the left, give leave to adde a <hi>word</hi> or two of <hi>Direction</hi> now in the cloſe, for your better improvement of the doctrine.</p>
               <p>It is tw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold. <hi>ſc.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. A word of <hi>Caution.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. A word of <hi>Comfort,</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Caution
<list>
                     <item>1. To all in general.</item>
                     <item>2. To the Saints in particular.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To all in generall.</head>
               <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Caution general.</hi>
                  </note> take heed of <hi>miſtaking your infirmities:</hi> take heed of putting a <hi>ſofter name</hi> upon your Corruptions, then <hi>God</hi> doth, and the <hi>Scripture</hi> doth; this is the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral deceit amongſt Chriſtians; <hi>Sin takes ſanctuary under infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity.</hi> Every wicked man calls his <hi>Iuſts</hi> his groſs ſins, his infirmities. The <hi>Drunkard</hi> ſayes, it is my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity, the <hi>Swearer</hi> ſayes, it is my infirmity, the Adulterer, alas! what would you have him do? it is his infirmity, <hi>&amp; ſic in caeteris.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:170519:59"/>
               <p>Every prophane wretched miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creant hath taken hold of the <hi>horns</hi> of the Altar, and there he cries, alas, <hi>this is my infirmity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Brethren, take heed, ſay not <hi>infirmity,</hi> when it is <hi>more then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>When is that?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When ſin is more then infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. When men are <hi>more ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous for pardon then for Cure;</hi> they are more then infirmities: if pardon alone would quiet thy ſpirit without healing, thou art under a <hi>mortall diſeaſe.</hi> The Saints cry, <hi>heal me O Lord, and I ſhall be healed:</hi> and this is an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of their ſincerity; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of pardon only argueth <hi>Self-Love,</hi> deſire of Cure argueth <hi>love to Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> deſire of <hi>pardon,</hi> argueth men <hi>fear hell</hi> only, but deſire of <hi>healing</hi> argueth men <hi>fear God;</hi> defire of pardon only ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth men would be content to live in ſin <hi>if they durſt;</hi> deſire of Cure
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170519:60"/>ſhewes men would not live in ſin, if they might.</p>
               <p>Secondly, much more, <hi>when men ſtudy the ſatisfaction of their luſts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In exordio adoleſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trae petie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram à te caſtitatem &amp; conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentiam, &amp;c.</note> more then the <hi>mortification</hi> of them; they are <hi>more</hi> then <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities: Auguſtine</hi> confeſſeth of himſelf before Coverſion, he prayed (ſometimes) for the <hi>gift of chaſtity;</hi> but there was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing within that ſecretly whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered,
<note place="margin">Timebam ſi ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>citò exaudires &amp; ſanares me à mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo boncu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>entiae, quam ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleri ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebam quam ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingui.</note> 
                  <hi>not yet Lord;</hi> for ſayes he, <hi>I was afraid, leſt God ſhould hear me too ſoon, and cure in me that diſtemper which I had rather ſhould have been ſaisfied, then mortified.</hi> This is the temper of every unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate perſon: <hi>Conviction</hi> may make them <hi>pray</hi> againſt their luſts ſometime, but <hi>love of ſin</hi> makes them <hi>indulge</hi> them: they cannot find in their hearts to lay violent hands upon them, they be yet as their <hi>own fleſh,</hi> and <hi>no man ever yet hated his own fleſh, but nouriſheth, and cheriſheth it,</hi> when men are ſo tenderly affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, to their Corruptions,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170519:60"/>they are <hi>more then infirmities;</hi> ſin <hi>reigns,</hi> when men dare not <hi>diſpleaſe it,</hi> nor riſe up in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition againſt it.</p>
               <p>Thirdly,
<note place="margin">Third note of reigning ſin.</note> ſin is <hi>more then infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity,</hi> when men <hi>are impatient of Conviction;</hi> when men are ſo ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of their corruptions, that a man muſt not touch them; <hi>He that toucheth them, toucheth the apple of their eyes.</hi> Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hearts are glad of conviction; <hi>let the righteous ſmite me,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 141.</note> it ſhall be a precious oyle,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>When reproof is a <hi>wound</hi> which men cannot bear, it is a ſign ſin is alive, and whole within them. Sin is then <hi>King</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſoul,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 8.4.</note> when a man muſt not ſay unto it, <hi>what doſt thou?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 3.31.</note> and <hi>againſt which there is no riſing up.</hi> The more any corruption is indulged, the leſſe infirmitie is in it.</p>
               <p>Fourthly,
<note place="margin">Fourth note.</note> when a man or a woman is <hi>never troubled with their corruptions, but when wrath is upon them,</hi> then they are <hi>more then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities.</hi> The godly go mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170519:61"/>under their <hi>ſecret corruptions,</hi> when the Sun ſhines upon their Tabernacles with the warmeſt influences, yea when God is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſhine into their hearts, with the cleareſt beams of love; the more ſenſible the Saints are of <hi>Gods love,</hi> the more they <hi>hate</hi> their own corruptions, becauſe they make them <hi>unlike to God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They that are never troubled with corruption, but when wrath is upon them, it is <hi>wrath</hi> that troubles them, and not <hi>corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> this is not infirmity. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal people are never good but when they are <hi>under the rod:</hi> and then, not becauſe their <hi>ſins diſpleaſe God,</hi> but becauſe Gods <hi>judgements diſpleaſe them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fiftly, when Infirmities <hi>ſerve men only for apologies,</hi> they are <hi>more</hi> then <hi>infirmities,</hi> when a man can ſay of <hi>any corruption, it is my infirmity, and acquieſce there,</hi> it is very dangerous. This is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, men (in nature) do not ſit down patient under infirmities,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170519:61"/>becauſe infirmities, Corruption is <hi>all wed</hi> where infirmity is the <hi>apology,</hi> and <hi>allowed</hi> corruption is more then infirmity: The Saints infirmites are their <hi>afflictions,</hi> their <hi>burdens,</hi> not their apologies. <hi>Oh wretch that I am,
<note place="margin">Rom 7.24.</note> who ſhall deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver me?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Sixthly,
<note place="margin">Sixth note.</note> when <hi>the heart is more offended at the Law,</hi> becauſe it croſſeth corruption, <hi>then at cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption,</hi> becauſe it croſſeth the Law, it is <hi>more then infirmity.</hi> Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſouls <hi>juſtify the Law,</hi> but <hi>condemn</hi> their <hi>luſts;
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.12. Verſe 14.</note> the Law is holy, and the Commandement is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and juſt, and good:</hi> all the fault they find, is <hi>with themſelves; I am carnal ſold under ſin:</hi> they have <hi>good thoughts</hi> of the law; it is good, it is <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> but they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not find any word bad enough for <hi>themſelves. I am a wretch,</hi> &amp;c. this is <hi>infirmity</hi> indeed. It is good when men ſtudy to <hi>bring up</hi> their <hi>hearts</hi> to the <hi>Rule,</hi> &amp; not labour to <hi>bring down</hi> the <hi>Rule</hi> to their <hi>hearts:</hi> Gods children would feign have
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170519:62"/>
                  <hi>their lives as ſtrait as the Law.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 119.5.</note> Oh <hi>that my wayes were directed to keep thy Satutes,</hi> carnal people would willingly have <hi>the Law as crooked as their lives:
<note place="margin">Ezek. 18.</note> The wayes of the Lord are not equall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This is an hard ſaying,
<note place="margin">Joh. 6.</note> who can bear it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly,
<note place="margin">Seventh note.</note> when <hi>Corruption gets ground,</hi> and growes more impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and head-ſtrong from time to time; it is then <hi>more</hi> then <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity:</hi> when ſin fortifieth it ſelf, and can make reſiſtance againſt whatſoever doth oppoſe it, it is <hi>Reigning ſin,</hi> ſin then in the foul, is as <hi>Rex in Regno;</hi> as a King in his Kingdome; ſtrengthening and ſecuring its throne againſt all oppoſition. Corruption in the Saints is upon the loſing-hand; <hi>infirmities</hi> will grow more and more <hi>infirm:</hi> as diſtempers in the body, when a man is upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> Then are not <hi>my cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions</hi> infirmities, will ſome poore ſoule be ready to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject;
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170519:62"/>for they grow <hi>ſtronger and ſtronger,</hi> and not weaker and weaker; my ſinful paſſions, and <hi>diſtempers,</hi> get ground of <hi>me, I do not</hi> get ground of <hi>my paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſw. <hi>To this I anſwer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">I. It is not uſuall for them that lye under the power and command of their <hi>luſts,</hi> to make ſuch complaints; they of whom luſt and corruption gets ground, ſeldome <hi>ſay ſo;</hi> they ſtudy apologies, <hi>(ut ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra)</hi> not aggravations. Such poor Chriſtians therefore that thus object againſt themſelves, are not eaſily to be believed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is true, Satan may roare moſt, when he is caſt out; the laſt pangs of dying beaſts are ſtrongeſt, and ſo it may be with a dying luſt.</p>
               <p>But, obſerve a few things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Many times, the poor belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaies, <hi>his corruptions grow,</hi> when onely indeed <hi>he growes more ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of his corruptions:</hi> when <hi>light</hi>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:170519:63"/>groweth, and <hi>grace</hi> groweth, and corruption growes <hi>more burden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom:</hi> this <hi>doubting Souls,</hi> call the groweth of corruption: the new Convert, complains he <hi>hath</hi> more corruption, then ever; when onely he <hi>ſees</hi> corruption more then ever, and is <hi>more ſenſible</hi> of corruption then ever. Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs this, that the poor Soul is more impatient now of the leaſt corruption, then formerly it was of the groſſeſt acts: this is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, the more burdenſome cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption groweth, the more ground it loſeth.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Doth thy <hi>diſplacency</hi> againſt corruption grow? Doſt thou <hi>hate thy corruptions</hi> more then ever, &amp; thy ſelf for them? Whilſt thou ſaieſt, corruption growes, doſt thou diſlike thy corruptions more then ever? Chriſtian, thou getteſt ground of corruption, corruption doth not get ground of thee. A Tyrant may grow more oppreſſive and more impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, but he growes more <hi>bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſom</hi>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:170519:63"/>and more <hi>intollerable.</hi> Why all this while he is upon the loſing hand; he loſeth ground in <hi>the hearts</hi> of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: Let him think himſelf ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo ſecure, <hi>he is upon the decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning hand;</hi> he is <hi>afalling.</hi> So it is with ſin; the more it is <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> the <hi>weaker it groweth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, Doth thy <hi>watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> grow? Thou <hi>grow more vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilant,</hi> more <hi>jealous</hi> of thine own heart? More <hi>afraid</hi> of thy ſelf? Doſt ſtand at a <hi>greater di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> from temptation, ſhunning the appearances and occaſions of ſin? <hi>Corruption gets no ground of thee, but thou of Corruption?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, Doth thy <hi>oppoſition grow?</hi> As corruption and temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation growes ſtronger (in thy apprehenſion) doſt thou make ſtronger <hi>reſiſtances,</hi> doſt thou <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie</hi> more againſt temptation? Doſt pray more and more <hi>fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vently?</hi> Art thou more and more <hi>active</hi> in the dutie of <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification? Corruption</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer.</p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:170519:64"/>
               <p>Fifthly, Doth <hi>Chriſt grow more precious</hi> to thee? Doſt thou ſee more <hi>need</hi> of Chriſt? More <hi>beauty</hi> and <hi>excellency</hi> in Chriſt; not onely for <hi>pardon</hi> of ſin, but for <hi>power</hi> againſt ſin? Not only for <hi>juſtification,</hi> but for <hi>ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation?</hi> Not onely as a fountain of <hi>happineſs,</hi> but as a fountain of <hi>holineſs?</hi> And doſt thou go out <hi>in his ſtrength</hi> againſt (thy cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions; labouring with the Apoſtle) <hi>to know the power of his Reſurrection,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>. 3.10.</note> and the fellowſhip of his ſufferings, that thou mayeſt be conformable to him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fear not, Chriſtian, <hi>thy God and the God of thy fathers, hath given thee treaſure in thy ack.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Care con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcit adverſus ſpiritum, ſi non &amp; ſpiritus aderſus carnem fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciunt adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e ium.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ug. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Gal. 1.5, 7.</note>
               </p>
               <p>It is a bleſſed thing when cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption drawes out grace; when, as <hi>the fleſh luſteth againſt the ſpirit, the ſpirit luſteth againſt the fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Behold, whilſt thou mourneſt and complaineſt that <hi>corruption gets ground;</hi> the truth is, Grace gets <hi>ground, of Corruption: Sence of corruption</hi> is a grace, and <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicency</hi>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:170519:64"/>againſt corruption is a grace, and <hi>watchfulneſs</hi> is a grace, and <hi>oppoſition</hi> againſt ſin is a grace, and <hi>precious thoughts of Chriſt a grace.</hi> Now if corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be an occaſion to exert theſe graces, it is <hi>grace</hi> that <hi>gets ground</hi> of corruption, and not <hi>corruption</hi> of grace.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſecond general Caution.
<note place="margin">A ſecond general Caution.</note>
               </head>
               <p>Take heed of making <hi>the Saints infirmities, your encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in ſin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For firſt, <hi>They are not for our imitation,</hi> but our <hi>admonition,</hi> Ut ſup. uſe. 1. make not the infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of the <hi>godly,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cur non ego?</hi> Salvian.</note> patrons</hi> of your <hi>wickedneſs.</hi> Say not in your hearts, <hi>why not I?</hi> Why may not I be <hi>drunk</hi> as well as <hi>Noah?</hi> And commit adultery as well as <hi>David?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>There is no ſuch folly in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;</hi> was there ever any ſo ſottiſh as to imitate other mens defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities in nature, or misfortunes in the world? Did ye ever hear
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170519:65"/>of any man ſo mad, as to put out his eyes, becauſe another man was blind? Or to throw away his riches, becauſe other men are poor?</p>
               <p>Was ever any man yet heard to ſay, And why may not I <hi>ſit upon the dungh-hil</hi> as well as Job? Or lye at the rich mans door <hi>begging,</hi> as well as <hi>Lazarus?</hi> Why may not I dwell in the wilderneſs as well as <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt? And not have whereon to lay my head as well as our Saviour?</p>
               <p>Alas, Alas! that this folly ſhould onely befal the ſons of men onely in <hi>ſpirituals,</hi> in <hi>ſoul-concernments! This is a lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſhall be for a lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>There be in the Saints of God things more worthy of imitation then their infirmities.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There was <hi>meekneſs</hi> in <hi>Moſes, patience</hi> in <hi>Job, holineſs</hi> in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid; zeal for God</hi> in <hi>Elijah;</hi> &amp;c. In a word, there are <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in Gods children</hi> as well as cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions:
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170519:65"/>Oh! how much more noble and excellent is it to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the Saints in their graces then in their <hi>infirmities?</hi> This were <hi>wiſdom,</hi> to pick out that which is praiſe worthy,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.1</note> and <hi>be followers of them as they are fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of Chriſt!</hi> Every fool and baſe ſpirit can imitate the worſt part in men; what a ſordid criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſm was it in him, that read over <hi>Homer, onely to find out his faults?</hi> A wiſe generous ſpirit will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve what is <hi>honourable</hi> and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 4.8.</note> and ſet up that for his <hi>ſtandard,</hi> and exemplar. You take notice of the <hi>Saints falls;</hi> but why do ye not take notice alſo of their <hi>riſing again?</hi> You ſee their <hi>ſins;</hi> but why are ye blind to their <hi>repentance,</hi> their <hi>tears,</hi> their <hi>broken bones,</hi> their <hi>ſelf-judging,</hi> their <hi>reſtleſs inquietude of ſpirit,</hi> till <hi>God</hi> be <hi>reconciled</hi> to them?</p>
               <p>Their <hi>infirmities</hi> were but <hi>few,</hi> their <hi>graces many;</hi> their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities <hi>rare,</hi> their graces <hi>habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual:</hi>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:170519:66"/>Here's work, Chriſtian, for your imitation.</p>
               <p>Your would have <hi>Abrahams riches:</hi> oh! labour to get <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams faith:</hi> you would be like <hi>David</hi> in <hi>honour,</hi> be like him in <hi>holineſs:</hi> you would have <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lijah's power,</hi> to call down fire from Heaven; labour to poſſeſs <hi>Elijah</hi> his <hi>zeal,</hi> his <hi>courage,</hi> his <hi>prayerfulneſs.</hi> This is excellent! ſtudy the graces you ſee in other men, not their infirmities.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Laſtly, Conſider, <hi>your ſins will be never the leſs, becauſe other mens infirmities are great:</hi> He that maketh light of ſin be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Saints have their infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities; to be ſure <hi>is no Saint</hi> himſelf; and his corruptions are no longer <hi>infirmities,</hi> but <hi>allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed preſumptions.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Take a third Caution.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inſult not over the Saints of God,
<note place="margin">A third general Caution.</note> becauſe of their infirmities.</hi> For conſider,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Thou <hi>ſeeſt their infirmities;</hi>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:170519:66"/>their failings; thou ſeeſt not <hi>what they coſt them.</hi> Little doſt thou know what broken bones, what ſharp corrections, what bleeding Souls, what buckets of tears they pour out before the Lord,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 73.22.</note> becauſe of their corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. <hi>Oh! wretch that I am!</hi> &amp;c. How do they ſhame them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves before the Lord for their failings? <hi>So fooliſh was, I and ſo ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, and like a beaſt before thee;</hi> they cannot find language bad enough to revile themſelves withall in Gods preſence.</p>
               <p>Surely if thou didſt know what the Saints infirmities coſt them, thou wouldſt reflect upon thy ſelf, and be aſhamed; and ſmiting upon thy breſt cry out with ſelf-abhorrency, oh! wretch that I am; I have <hi>ſinned</hi> as theſe ſervants of God have done, but I have never <hi>mourned</hi> as they have done: I have <hi>ſinned</hi> as <hi>David,</hi> but I have not <hi>repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> as <hi>David:</hi> I have denied Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt with <hi>Peter,</hi> but I have
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170519:67"/>not with <hi>Peter wept bitterly;;</hi> my <hi>heart</hi> hath been a fountain of <hi>ſin,</hi> but my <hi>head</hi> hath not been a fountain of <hi>tears:</hi> I have been <hi>viler in Gods eyes</hi> then ever they were, but I was never ſo <hi>vile in mine own eyes</hi> as they have been; The Saints infirmities are their <hi>afflictions,</hi> but my corruptions have been my <hi>delight: God be merciful to me a ſinner:</hi> What cauſe have I to <hi>mourn,</hi> rather then to <hi>inſult,</hi> and <hi>cenſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, Turn in upon thy ſelf, and thou ſhalt find <hi>more cauſe of judging thy ſelf</hi> then thy <hi>brother.</hi> He hath his <hi>weakneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> thou haſt thy <hi>wilfulneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</hi> He his <hi>failings,</hi> ſometimes, thou thy <hi>groſs falls</hi> (poſſibly) every day; He is <hi>ſurprized</hi> by a temptation; thou goeſt forth to meet <hi>temptation:</hi> Yea, to <hi>tempt</hi> temptation, to tempt the <hi>devil,</hi> to <hi>tempt thee;</hi> Yea, thou thy ſelf art <hi>a tempter</hi> to others, ſinning and cauſing others to ſin: and ſo doeſt the devils work, &amp;c.
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170519:67"/>
                  <hi>and doſt thou judge thy brother? Thou hypocrite,
<note place="margin">Matth. 7.5.</note> caſt firſt the beam out of thine eye, and then ſhalt thou ſee clearly to caſt out the mote out of thy brothers eye.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>timur perſpicillis magis quam ſpeculis.</hi> Sen.</note> What is the <hi>mote</hi> of <hi>infirmity,</hi> to the <hi>beam</hi> of <hi>Preſumption?</hi> Be more in thy <hi>looking glaſs,</hi> and thou wilt have leſs uſe of thy <hi>ſpectacles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, Know this, oh man! who ever thou art; that in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry act of <hi>judging thy brother, thou condemneſt thy ſelf:</hi> Thy <hi>cenſures</hi> of thy <hi>brothers infirmities</hi> are ſo many <hi>aggravations</hi> of thine own <hi>wickedneſſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If his <hi>mote</hi> ſinck him ſo deep in <hi>thy judgment,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 7 2</note> how deep will thy <hi>beam</hi> ſinck thee in <hi>Gods? With what meaſure thou meteſt, it ſhall be meaſured to thee again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take heed and prepare not ſtripes for thine own back. God wil not judge his people for their <hi>infirmities,</hi> but God will judge thee for thy <hi>preſumptuous ſins:</hi> yea,
<note place="margin">Rom. 2.1, 2.</note> God will <hi>judge thee for judging thy brother,</hi> and wo unto
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170519:68"/>thee when God cometh to judge thee;
<note place="margin">Luke 19.22.</note> 
                  <hi>Doſt not thou fear God, ſeeing thou art in the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation? Ex ore tuo,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>out of thine own mouth, thou ſhalt be judged, thou wicked ſervant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, It is much more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable to <hi>mourn with the Saints,</hi> and to mourn <hi>for them,</hi> then to judge and cenſure them. Their infirmities are their bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den; a burden (the Lord knows) which they are not able to bear: by <hi>ſympathy</hi> and compaſſion thou mighteſt help to <hi>bear their bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> by reproach and cenſure thou <hi>addeſt</hi> to it; a cruelty which in a leſſer <hi>model</hi> God doth ſeverely threaten, <hi>Zech.</hi> 11.15. And thus much for the Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in general.</p>
               <p>In particular this doctrine may adminiſter <hi>Caution to the Saints themſelves.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cautions to the Saints. 1. Caution</note>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, Although corruptions in the Saints be but <hi>infirmities,</hi> yet let even the beſt of Gods Saints, learn
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:170519:68"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>To <hi>Mourn</hi> for their Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</item>
                     <item>To <hi>Watch</hi> over their Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</item>
                     <item>To <hi>Pray</hi> againſt their Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>There is a ſecret deceit in our hearts, and Satan ſets on the temptation;
<note place="margin">Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities.</note> 
                  <hi>What need I be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled and ſollicitous about my cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions?</hi> They are <hi>but infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities,</hi> and the beſt of Gods Saints have their infirmities, and many, <hi>greater</hi> then <hi>mine</hi> be: upon this very accompt many grow <hi>ſecure,</hi> and are <hi>at eaſe in Zion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay but conſider,</p>
               <p n="1">1. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſ. </seg>1</label> Such reaſonings and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, are <hi>no good-ſigns;</hi> when <hi>ſin takes ſanctuary</hi> under <hi>infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> it is to be ſuſpected of <hi>more then infirmity, I</hi> know Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan is buſie, &amp; the heart deceitful, <hi>ut ſup.</hi> but ſuch diſcourſes, yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to and reſted in, may juſtly cauſe a man to fear his heart is not ſound with God.</p>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:170519:69"/>
               <p>Secondly, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſ. </seg>2</label> Conſider, Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in the Saints are of the <hi>ſame nature</hi> with the <hi>luſts of wicked men.</hi> It is <hi>ſin,</hi> though it be not <hi>reigning</hi> ſin: and this is enough to break a gracious heart to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider thus with it ſelf; my cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption is my <hi>infirmity</hi> indeed: I, but not ſuch an infirmity, as a <hi>dim eye,</hi> or a <hi>palſie hand,</hi> or a <hi>lame foot,</hi> &amp;c. They are but <hi>natural defects:</hi> my <hi>pride,</hi> my <hi>paſſion,</hi> my <hi>love of the world,</hi> theſe are <hi>ſinful diſtempers:</hi> they, do but preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice the <hi>body,</hi> theſe defile my Soul; And look what ever may be ſaid of ſin in general, as that it is a <hi>tranſgreſſion</hi> of Gods <hi>Law,</hi> a <hi>contrariety</hi> unto Gods <hi>Nature,</hi> a <hi>contradiction</hi> to Gods <hi>Will;</hi> A <hi>practical blaſphemy</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his <hi>Name,</hi> and <hi>Attributes,</hi> the <hi>rape</hi> of his <hi>mercies,</hi> the <hi>date</hi> of his <hi>juſtice;</hi> the <hi>challenge</hi> of his <hi>power,</hi> the <hi>blind</hi> of his <hi>om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience;</hi> It gives the <hi>lye</hi> to Gods <hi>truth,</hi> and the <hi>fool</hi> to his <hi>wiſdom;</hi> This, and all this, and
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170519:69"/>much more may be affirmed of the <hi>ſinful diſtempers</hi> of my heart: the leaſt corruption in my curſed nature, would <hi>ungod God;</hi> if my ſin could help it, God ſhould be God no longer. A man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not give <hi>ſin</hi> a worſe name then <hi>it ſelf;</hi> &amp; as a man cannot give the <hi>greateſt</hi> ſin, <hi>a worſe</hi> name then <hi>ſin;</hi> ſo he cannot give the <hi>leaſt</hi> ſin a <hi>better.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is no difference in the <hi>nature of ſin</hi> in the godly and in the wicked: all the difference is in their <hi>perſons;</hi> the one is regenerate, the other is not; but ſin remains ſin ſtill, in the one as well as in the other. Is not this matter of <hi>deep humiliation,</hi> to the Saints?</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſ. </seg>3</label> As infirmities in the godly are of the ſame <hi>nature,</hi> ſo they are of the <hi>ſame merit</hi> with <hi>ſin</hi> in the <hi>wicked.</hi> All ſin is <hi>damning.</hi> And thus ſhould the children of God, <hi>Smiting upon their thighs,</hi> ſay in Gods preſence, <hi>It were juſt with God to damn me
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:170519:70"/>for my infirmities.</hi> And that he doth not, is not from the <hi>ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my ſin,</hi> but from the <hi>great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his mercy;</hi> not from the <hi>nature</hi> of my <hi>ſin,</hi> but from the <hi>goodneſs of his nature:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 23.5.</note> not <hi>BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE they are but infirmities,</hi> but <hi>BECA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE</hi> He hath <hi>made with me an everlaſting Covenant, ordered in all things and ſure.</hi> Is not this an humbling conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration?</p>
               <p>Fourthly, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſ. </seg>4</label> Not leſs, <hi>this,</hi> ſc. that <hi>the Saints infirmities grieve the Spirit of God.</hi> Indeed they are infirmities which <hi>properly</hi> may be ſaid to grieve Gods Spirit: the <hi>groſs ſins</hi> of wicked men, they are ſaid to <hi>quench</hi> the Spirit, and <hi>vex</hi> the Spirit, and <hi>deſpite</hi> the Spirit of God. The diſtempers that remain in the godly <hi>do grieve the Spirit;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.30. <hi>Res deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata eſt Spiritus Sanctus.</hi> Tert.</note> even of thoſe who are by that Spirit <hi>ſealed up to the day of redemption:</hi> Gods Spirit is a <hi>tender, ſweet, delicate thing.</hi> A tender dear friend is properly grieved by <hi>unkindneſſes:</hi>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:170519:70"/>the <hi>injuries</hi> of <hi>enemies</hi> do <hi>provoke,</hi> the <hi>diſpleaſures</hi> of friends do <hi>grieve</hi> and <hi>diſquiet.</hi> This ſhould touch a Saint to the quick, <hi>to grieve his
<note n="*" place="margin">If he grieve his Cemforter, who ſhall comfort him!</note> Comforter.</hi> The Holy Ghoſt delighteth to take up his habitation in a Sedate loving ſpirit.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſ. </seg>5</label> The Saints infirmities are ſo many <hi>abatements of their Excellencies;</hi> oh what glorious creatures would the Saints be, were it not for their <hi>pride,</hi> and for their <hi>paſſion,</hi> for their <hi>love of the world,</hi> and for their <hi>impatience!</hi> Et ſic in caeteris.</p>
               <p>They would be more then <hi>men, Angels incarnate,</hi> and <hi>glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Saints,</hi> before, <hi>glorified.</hi> It is their <hi>diſtempers</hi> which do ſo <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe</hi> them many times, that they are hardly known from other men. The Saints infirmities, are the dead <hi>fly</hi> in the <hi>Apothecaries ointment;</hi> the unſavory <hi>But,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccl. 10.4.</note> in their commendations; a good man, but <hi>cholerick;</hi> an holy wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, but <hi>high-ſpirited,</hi> &amp;c. thus
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:170519:71"/>infirmities are <hi>a veyle</hi> to a Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians beauty, and the <hi>flye-blow</hi> to their reputation.</p>
               <p>Let your light ſhine as bright as the <hi>Sun</hi> in the Firmament, your infirmities will <hi>eclipſe</hi> them, and darken their glory.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſ. </seg>6</label> The Saints infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, may, and ſometimes, do, <hi>darken their Evidences:</hi> ſinful af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections eſpecially, if <hi>indulged,</hi> may <hi>hinder aſſurance,</hi> and keep the ſoul under jealouſies and doubtings: a <hi>Barly-corn</hi> layd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>ball of the eye,</hi> will hinder the <hi>ſight of the Sun,</hi> as well as a <hi>Mountain,</hi> and <hi>the leaſt hair will caſt its ſhadow.</hi> They are believers <hi>infirmities,</hi> which keep them ſo <hi>low</hi> in <hi>comfort;</hi> and make them ſo oft <hi>call their eſtate into queſtion;</hi> crying out with that good woeman:
<note place="margin">Gen. 24.22.</note> 
                  <hi>If it be ſo, why am I thus?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Had they not need to watch over their infirmities?</p>
               <p>Is this a <hi>ſmall evil</hi> in the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt ſin, that it <hi>hinders our aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:170519:71"/>and intercepts between the <hi>ſoul</hi> and the <hi>light of Gods counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, which is better then life it ſelf?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seventhly, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſ. </seg>7</label> The infirmities of the godly (when they doe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear) <hi>obſtruct their influences;</hi> and, not ſeldom, render their endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of doing good <hi>ineffectual:</hi> while the ſence of their infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, <hi>quickens</hi> their <hi>endeavours,</hi> the <hi>notice</hi> which ſtanders-by take of them, <hi>hinders</hi> their ſucceſſe. It is enough to the proud world to reject and ſcorn the meekeſt and counſels of the godly, if they can ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve but the leaſt failing in them: The Saints infirmities are wicked mens ſhields, whereby they fence themſelves againſt their holy ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions, as if they were ſo many <hi>poyſoned darts and arrowes;</hi> they need not reprove me, they are as bad themſelves; they can <hi>do thus and thus:</hi> as if the Saints <hi>weakneſſes</hi> would juſtifie their own <hi>wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes.</hi> Yea, not only ſo, but to
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:170519:72"/>aggravate their own guilt: wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men look upon the Saints fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings with the <hi>multiplying end</hi> of the glaſſe which repreſents them in a <hi>bigger character,</hi> then they are in themſelves; and, not ſeldom, retort a tender reproof with a cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell reproach;
<note place="margin">Mat 7.6.</note> 
                  <hi>wounding</hi> thoſe that intend <hi>their Cure;</hi> and like ſwine, <hi>trampling the pearle under foot, turn again and rent them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As thus in generall, ſo more particularly, <hi>Paſſion</hi> in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prover is a great <hi>prejudice</hi> to the <hi>reproof;</hi> a man ſeldom doth good in anger,
<note place="margin">Jam.</note> 
                  <hi>the wrath of man</hi> work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not the <hi>righteouſneſſe of God:</hi> mans anger ſeldom attains Gods righteous ends; the worſt ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient we can put into good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, is <hi>wrath;</hi> partly, becauſe paſſion doth <hi>blind the judgement,</hi> and diſcompoſe reaſon; a man in anger ſees not where his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage lieth.</p>
               <p>Partly, becauſe anger acted beyond Scripture-limits, is not a ſuitable inſtrument for the meek
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:170519:72"/>ſpirit of God, to uſe: The God of peace delights to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour quiet and compoſed ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits.</p>
               <p>Partly and eſpecially, becauſe the proud world will not bear it: behold they will hardly ſuffer the touch of the ſofteſt and tendereſt hand, (do but <hi>touch</hi> theſe <hi>moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and they will ſmoke;</hi>) how much leſſe will they bear it, if ye ſmite them with a rod of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did the Rock, with an <hi>hear ye Rebels?</hi> they will not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure oyle to be dropt into their wounds; how will they endure the bitter <hi>Corraſive?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In all theſe reſpects the Saints of God had need to watch over their paſſions; anger is not always ſo juſt and righteous as it ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be; we <hi>know not of what ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit we are:</hi> As the world is ready to call zeal paſſion; ſo we are very prone to call our paſſion zeal too often: and therefore it is not to be truſted without much holy care &amp; jealouſie over our ſpirits,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170519:73"/>
                  <hi>leſt our goud be evill ſpoken of.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Eighthly, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſ. </seg>8</label> The paſſions which are in the ſervants of God, do many times <hi>render their Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes leſſe acceptable to their brethren;</hi> by giving way to their own di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers, they oft become bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens to others, and to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves too;
<note place="margin">Jer. 20.3, 4.</note> very <hi>MAGOR MISSABIBS, a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour to themſelves and their friends.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This ſhould make them ride their paſſions with a very ſtrict rein; leſt they tranſport them out into indecent exceſſes, &amp; commotions of ſpirit; to the diſhonour of the Goſpel, and the grief of the godly.</p>
               <p>Ninthly, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſ. </seg>9</label> The <hi>more infirmity,</hi> the <hi>leſſe grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Tenthly, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſ. </seg>10</label> But the more <hi>ſence of infirmity,</hi> the <hi>more grace.</hi> To be ſenſible of the leaſt corruption, and to mourn over it, argues a <hi>tender conſcience,</hi> and ſtrength of grace. A ſound eye cannot endure the leaſt <hi>mote</hi> in it, nor a
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170519:73"/>tender conſcience, the leaſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filement:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Oh purge me from my ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret ſins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Eleventhly, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſ. </seg>11</label> and yet this is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of greater weight, that <hi>Infirmities neglected may grow to dangerous diſeaſes;</hi> as we ſee in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, a <hi>cold</hi> neglected may grow to a burning <hi>fever;</hi> a <hi>diſtillati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> from the head upon the lungs, if ſlighted, may turn to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, &amp;c. and ſo in the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall conſtitution, a leſſer cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption not timely reſiſted and mortified, may grow to be an head-ſtrong luſt, which in the very godly ſhall keep grace at <hi>an under,</hi> and make the Chriſtian go halting to his grave. <hi>It is good to deal with our infirmities betimes.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Obſta principiis.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Twelfthly, And laſtly, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſ. </seg>12</label> to be ſure, ſpiritual <hi>infirmities may bring temporal judgements upon</hi> the Saints. <hi>Moſes</hi> his <hi>paſſion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Num. 20.12.</note> made him <hi>fall ſhort</hi> of the <hi>promiſed land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Davids</hi> ſurprize into <hi>murder
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:170519:74"/>and adultery, entails the ſword upon him and his family</hi> to all ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations.
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 12.10. Luk. 1.20.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Zechariah <hi>his unbelief</hi> ſtrikes him <hi>dumb</hi> for a ſeaſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eli</hi> his <hi>indulgence to his Sons,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 3.13. <hi>Cum</hi> ch 4.18.</note> betrayes the <hi>Ark</hi> into the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies hand, and then breaks his own <hi>neck.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Davids <hi>pride</hi> in a <hi>numerous peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 24.15.</note> coſts <hi>him the lives of</hi> 70 <hi>thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſubjects.</hi> And <hi>Hezekiah</hi> his <hi>unthankfulneſs</hi> brought <hi>wrath upon himſelf, and all Iſrael.</hi> 2 Chr. 32.25.</p>
               <p>This is a ſtartling conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 1.10. <hi>Strong in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities may bring ſtrong af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions.</hi>
                  </note> that though the Lord Jeſus hath delivered his Redeemed <hi>from wrath to come:</hi> yet their very infirmities may lay them, and their families, under the bitter fruits of Gods <hi>righteous diſpleaſure</hi> in this life; God <hi>THEREBY</hi> vindicating his own <hi>impartiality,</hi> his <hi>hatred againſt ſin,</hi> &amp; his <hi>unchangeable love</hi> to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>in chaſtening them here, that they may not be condemned with the world.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:170519:74"/>
               <head>And thus much for the firſt Caution. I ſhall adde a few more, very briefly.</head>
               <p>Secondly, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Caut. </seg>2</label> Be <hi>tender</hi> to your <hi>brethrens infirmities,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">to the Saints.</note> but <hi>ſevere</hi> to your <hi>own;</hi> this argues an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſpirit, when a Chriſtian <hi>ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravateth</hi> his <hi>own</hi> failings, but <hi>extenuates other</hi> mens; when he maketh <hi>complaints</hi> againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but <hi>apologies</hi> for his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren:
<note place="margin">Rom 7.24</note> 
                  <hi>I am a wretch ſold under ſin;</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle of himſelf, But as to other believers,
<note place="margin">Gal. 5.17.</note> 
                  <hi>The fleſh luſteth againſt the ſpirit, and the ſpirit againſt the fleſh, and theſe are contrary the one to the other, ſo that ye cannot do the things that ye would:</hi> It is the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſame apology, which our Lord Jeſus made for his <hi>ſleepy diſciples</hi> in the garden; <hi>the ſpirit is willing, but the fleſh is weak.</hi> True Saints have apologies for others, when they have none for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; they can <hi>juſtify</hi> others while they <hi>judge</hi> themſelves: the greateſt fault they find is
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:170519:75"/>with their own hearts. A true child of God is made up of <hi>Paſſion</hi> and <hi>Compaſſion;</hi> paſſion againſt <hi>himſelf,</hi> and Compaſſion towards his <hi>brethren;</hi> they <hi>condemn</hi> that in themſelves, which they can excuſe in another, yet not ſo as to <hi>ſuffer ſin upon their</hi> brethren. Conſciouſneſſe to our own Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions,
<note place="margin">Gal. 6.1.</note> ſhould make us <hi>tender of our brethren;</hi> but our <hi>love</hi> to the <hi>ſouls</hi> of our brethren, ſhould make us <hi>faithfull</hi> to them. A careleſſe paſſing by an <hi>offending brother,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Levit. 19.17.</note> is our <hi>ſin,</hi> not our love; and <hi>hatred,</hi> not compaſſion: we ſhould bear with one anothers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities: yet ſo as to be <hi>healers</hi> &amp; <hi>phyſitians,</hi> to their ſoul <hi>diſtempers,</hi> not <hi>acceſſories.</hi> It is a ſin, to ſpeak <hi>of our brethren,</hi> but it is our duty to ſpeak <hi>unto them;
<note place="margin">Heb. 3.13. <hi>It is a bleſſed thing to be of an heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and a restoring ſpirit.</hi>
                     </note> Exhort one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther daily, while it is called to day, leſt any of you be hardened, through the deceitfulneſs of ſin.</hi> The Lord reſtore this ſpirit to his people in <hi>England,</hi> or elſe we are like wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſpilt on the ground, that can
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:170519:75"/>never be gathered up again.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Caut. </seg>3</label> When you <hi>begin to be proud, mind your infirmities:</hi> when your <hi>parts</hi> or <hi>graces</hi> lift up your ſpirits, think of your <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions;</hi> and ſay thus to your ſelves, What, have I within me an <hi>hard heart,</hi> and ſhall I be <hi>proud?</hi> an <hi>earthly heart,</hi> and ſhall I be elated? a <hi>luſtfull heart,</hi> and ſhall I be puffed up? what, ſhall I be <hi>covetous</hi> and <hi>proud? paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</hi> and <hi>proud?</hi> poor (in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of grace) and proud? <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able</hi> to <hi>mortify</hi> any corruption, to ſtand before any temptation, to perform any holy duty, &amp; ſhall I be proud? eſpecially, this conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration added, <hi>nothing is mine own but my corruptions, my parts &amp; graces are Gods;</hi> concerning which I may ſay, as the young Prophet of his <hi>Axes head; alas, for they are but borrowed. What have I that I have not received?</hi> and if received, why do I glory? To be proud of that which is none of our own, is <hi>folly;</hi> but to be proud of that
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:170519:76"/>which is Gods, is <hi>ſacriledge.</hi> If therefore the ſence of <hi>Grace</hi> at any time lift you up; let the ſence of <hi>corruption pull you down.</hi> There is infinitely more in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption to humble, then there is in grace to <hi>elate</hi> and lift up the ſpirit.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Caut. </seg>4</label> 
                  <hi>Strive againſt your infirmities to the very death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> It may be, a poor deje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted ſoul may reply, I have <hi>ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> but I cannot <hi>prevaile;</hi> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption rather gets ground of <hi>me,</hi> then I of <hi>corruption.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To this complaint, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, what I ſaid before) I reply two things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Strive ſtill;</hi> for conſider, if corruption loſe no ground, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all thy <hi>wreſtlings</hi> and <hi>conflicts,</hi> what will it do if thou giveſt over ſtriving? if a man that rowes againſt the tide, <hi>get no ground,</hi> with <hi>plying his Oars,</hi> how will he be <hi>carried down the ſtream,</hi> if he ſtrike not a <hi>ſtroke?</hi> This thou muſt reſolve on, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:170519:76"/>
                  <hi>to overcome thy infirmities, or to be overcome by them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh do not throw away thy weapons, <hi>die not like a fool with thy hands bound:</hi> It is a kind of victory on this fide the grave, <hi>not to be driven out of the field;
<note place="margin">De gemi pugnare.</note> to die fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. If thy infirmities be too ſtrong for thee, <hi>Carry them to the croſs of Chriſt;</hi> remember, <hi>Victory muſt be fetcht out of Chriſts blood.</hi> This Crown is reſerved for the head of Chriſt, the <hi>King of Saints.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Victory is <hi>purchaſed,</hi> and Chriſt hath overcome already, in his own <hi>perſon:</hi> there is
<note n="*" place="margin">Phil. 3.10. Gal. 6.14. Eph. 1.2.</note> 
                  <hi>power</hi> in the death of Chriſt, as well as <hi>merit.</hi> And he that hath overcome <hi>for thee,</hi> on the <hi>Croſs;</hi> will <hi>overcome in</hi> thee by his <hi>ſpirit: becauſe grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is he that is in you, than he that is in the world.</hi> 1 Joh. 4.4. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, Chriſtian, act faith upon the <hi>merit,</hi> and upon the <hi>power</hi> of Chriſts <hi>Croſs,</hi> and <hi>believe</hi> down thy <hi>pride,</hi> and believe out thy <hi>paſsion,</hi> believe thy corruptions to death: <hi>Faithfull is he that
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:170519:77"/>hath promiſed, who alſe will do it.</hi> Let it not be the reproach of the Croſſe of Chriſt, that any cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption or luſt ſhould be too hard for it: no, there is <hi>enough,</hi> and a <hi>redundancie</hi> in Chriſt: only <hi>the Well is deep,</hi> and therefore thou muſt bring the bucket of faith to it; and then, with joy, <hi>thou mayſt draw water out of this Well of ſalvation.</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Caut. </seg>5</label> 
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, <hi>Be thankful,</hi> O ye Saints, &amp; ſervants of God, if, upon thoſe ſcriptural diſcoveries already laid down, <hi>you can evidence it to your own ſoules, that the remainders of corruption in your natures, are but infirmities:</hi> that ſin, of a <hi>Lord,</hi> is become a <hi>ſlave,</hi> and of an <hi>obeyed Soveraigne,</hi> is become a <hi>reſiſted Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant.</hi> Oh! it is matter of great thankfulneſs, that the <hi>dominion of ſin is broken;</hi> Although the Saints have cauſe to be humbled, <hi>that they have infirmities,</hi> cauſe to go mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the very death; yet they have infinite, cauſe to be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful that they are <hi>but infirmities;</hi> no longer domineering luſts, but
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:170519:77"/>baſe <hi>underlings,</hi> and vaſſals. And therefore, while the ſence of <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption</hi> maketh them complain, with the holy Apoſtle, <hi>Oh wretch that I am,</hi> &amp;c. the conſideration that <hi>ſin</hi> is <hi>dethroned,</hi> and remains now but as a <hi>blaſted infirmity</hi> in the ſoul, may cauſe them to triumph.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I thank God for Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> It was the <hi>merit of his Croſſe,</hi> that <hi>purchaſed</hi> this grace;
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.3.</note> Chriſt <hi>died</hi> that ſin might <hi>not live; He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemned ſin in the fleſh.</hi> He <hi>adjudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> ſin to death on his Croſſe, in his redeemed: And, by the <hi>power of his Croſſe he puts the ſentence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to execution:
<note place="margin">Gal. 5.24.</note> they that are Chriſts have crucified the fleſh with the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and luſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hence, <hi>that ſecurity</hi> given,
<note place="margin">Rom. 6.14.</note> 
                  <hi>ſin ſhall not reign in your mortal bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies;</hi> it is an <hi>Exhortation,</hi> verſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2. <hi>let not ſin reign:</hi> to ſhew it is our <hi>duty,</hi> to <hi>bring ſin to the Croſſe,</hi> to do execution upon every luſt; but it is a <hi>promiſe</hi> in the fourteenth verſe, <hi>ſin ſhall not reign,</hi> to aſſure the believer, that what Chriſt
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:170519:78"/>hath <hi>purchaſed</hi> with his <hi>blood,</hi> he will accompliſh by his <hi>Spirit:</hi> ſc. the final and total deſtruction of the body of ſin, whereof this is the pledge and firſt fruits, <hi>the dethro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of ſin in the ſoul,</hi> ſo that though it <hi>be,</hi> yet it ſhall not be as a Lord: ſin <hi>ſhall not reign in your mortal bodies: for ye are not under the Law but under Grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When the Lord turned again the Captivity of Zion,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 126.1, 2.</note> our mouth was fill'd with laughter, and our tongue with ſinging.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The redeemed ſoul hath not leſs cauſe to rejoyce, whoſe ſpiritual captivity the Lord hath turned, &amp; made them to <hi>lead Captivity</hi> cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive;
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.26.</note> to lead captive thoſe <hi>luſts, which led them</hi> captive before, <hi>take captive by the devil at his pleaſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So much for the Cautions.</p>
               <p>I come now in the laſt place to cloſe with the <hi>Comforts.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Comforts to the Saints e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their infirmities.</hi> 1. <hi>Comfort.</hi>
                  </note> Amongſt many take theſe:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Thy <hi>infirmities ſhall not preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice thy acceptance with God.</hi> This is a Chriſtians comfort, Though
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:170519:78"/>the world either through <hi>blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> cannot, or through <hi>malice</hi> will not diſtinguiſh between <hi>infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> and <hi>allowed wickedneſſe</hi> in the godly; yet, <hi>God</hi> both <hi>can,</hi> and <hi>will:</hi> He will diſtinguiſh between the <hi>Gold</hi> and the <hi>droſſe,</hi> between the <hi>chaffe</hi> and the <hi>wheat.</hi> He will not caſt away the gold, becauſe there is ſome droſſe mixt with it: nor throw the heap into the fire, becauſe there is much chaffe in it, if there be but ſome grains of good ſeed. God doth not caſt off his people, for their <hi>infirmities,</hi> when he finds any precions grains of <hi>ſincerity</hi> and <hi>grace</hi> in them. It is highly obſervable, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Sarah, David, Aſa, Jehoſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat,</hi> &amp;c. when the ſpirit of God comes in Scripture to give us their <hi>characters,</hi> he puts a <hi>veile</hi> upon their <hi>infirmities,</hi> and takes notice only of their <hi>graces.
<note place="margin">Gen. 17.12.</note> Sarah</hi> laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed through unbelief; yet, when the Holy Ghoſt makes mention of her in the New Teſtament, he takes notice only of her obedience and
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:170519:79"/>reverence to her husband: <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah obeyed Abraham,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.6.</note> and called him Lord. David</hi> had two terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>falls,</hi> able to make every one that readeth to tremble: but, in his character, God only takes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of his <hi>integrity,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 King 9.4.11.4, 6 14.8.</note> his <hi>perfection,</hi> the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſality of his obedience: He did ONLY that which was right in mine eyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Aſa <hi>had his failings,</hi> He was <hi>wroth</hi> with the <hi>Seer:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Chron. 16.10.</note> and again, <hi>In his ſickneſs he ſought not to the Lord, but to the Phyſitians,</hi> ver. 12. yet in the <hi>accompt of his reign,</hi> you find nothing,
<note place="margin">2 Chron. 14.17. 2 Chron. 20.35, 36.</note> but this high eulogie, The <hi>heart of</hi> Aſa <hi>was perfect all his days:</hi> And his ſon <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> contracted a <hi>wicked affinity,</hi> he left <hi>reformation imperfect,</hi> verſe 33. yet, in the <hi>ſumma totalis,</hi> he inherits the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of his <hi>Fathers ſincerity. He walked in the way of</hi> Aſa <hi>his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<note place="margin">2 Chron. 20.32.</note> and departed not from it, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that which was right in the ſight of the Lord.</hi> Oh what a Cordial is this for the fainting hearts of Gods dear children, ſinking un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:170519:79"/>the ſenſe of their corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? When God comes to weigh them in the ballance of the Sanctuary, he <hi>leaves out</hi> their <hi>infirmities;</hi> and <hi>puts</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing into the <hi>ſcales</hi> but their <hi>graces;</hi> He overlooks what is theirs, and takes notice, onely of <hi>what is his</hi> own; and ſo hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth them forth to the world as <hi>models of perfection.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God will <hi>not onely pardon,</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Com. </seg>2</label> but <hi>pitty the infirmities of his people.</hi> When their <hi>infirmities</hi> are their <hi>afflictions,</hi> they be the objects of <hi>Gods Compaſsion.</hi> Of all the children in the Family, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pitieth the <hi>weak child,</hi> the <hi>lame child,</hi> and the <hi>ſick child;</hi> when the poor child crieth, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>take</hi> me, Father <hi>help</hi> me, Father <hi>hold</hi> me, Father <hi>carry</hi> me; the Fathers bowels melt within him, and his compaſſions are rolled together; <hi>Like as a Father pitieth his children,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 103.13</note> ſo the Lord pitieth them that fear him.
<note place="margin">Iſa. 63 9.</note> In all their affliction he is
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:170519:80"/>afflicted, and the Angel of his preſence ſaveth them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When God ſeeth a poor belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſtriving, and wreſtling, and conflicting with his corruptions; weeping and mourning over them, like a dove of the valley; ſighing, with the breaking of his loins, and crying, <hi>Lord help, Lord rebuke</hi> my temptations, Lord, ſubdue my corruptions; plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and preſſing the promiſe, Lord, thou haſt ſaid, <hi>ſin ſhall not have dominion over me;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 6.14.</note> thou haſt ſaid, <hi>I will heal their back-ſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<note place="margin">Hoſ. 14.4.</note> I will love them freely,</hi> &amp;c. Why now Lord,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.49.</note> 
                  <hi>Remember the word unto thy ſervant upon which thou haſt cauſed me to hope;</hi> and, preſſing it again and again, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the ſervant of the Lord, oh! be it unto me according to thy word.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When God (I ſay) hears his poor <hi>Ephraims</hi> thus bemaoning themſelves,
<note place="margin">Jer. 31.19, 20.</note> and ſmiting upon their thigh, with holy ſhame and confuſion, reproach them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:170519:80"/>thus: <hi>Thou haſt chaſtiſed me and I was chaſtiſed;</hi> Lord, if blowes would have made me good, I had been good long ago; I have had affliction upon affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, ſtroke upon ſtroke; but all this while I have been <hi>as a bullock unaccuſtomed to the yoke,</hi> unteachable and untractable: thou haſt drawn forward, and I have drawn backward; thou haſt <hi>ſtricken</hi> me, &amp; I have <hi>kicked,</hi> I have lifted up the heel againſt thee; and hereupon, in an holy agony, turning Confeſſion into Prayer, <hi>Turn thou me and I ſhall be turned, heal me and I ſhall be bealed, for thou art the Lord my God;</hi> While thus (I ſay) the ſoul weeps, God weeps alſo; <hi>Ephraim</hi> weeps before God tears of <hi>contrition,</hi> and God weeps over <hi>Ephraim,</hi> tears of <hi>compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi> In all this affliction of the ſoul, Gods Soul is afflicted, his bowels are troubled, his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſions are kindled; and, as not able longer to refrain him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:170519:81"/>(as <hi>Joſeph</hi> once towards his brethren) he breaks out into this paſſionate condolency; <hi>Is Ephraim my dear Son?</hi> Is he a pleaſant child? Is this the voice of my repenting child, pouring out his Soul &amp; his ſorrowes over his ſinful in firmities? <hi>I do ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly remember him, I will ſurely have mercy upon him, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Com. </seg>3</label> In Caſe, your <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions</hi> be but your <hi>infirmities,</hi> they ſhall be <hi>no obſtruction to your prayers. David</hi> his unbelief did not prejudice the ſpeeding of his prayers; <hi>I ſaid I am caſt out of thy ſight, nevertheleſs, thou heardeſt the voice of my ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> Pſal. 31.32. Who would have thought that a prayer mixt with ſo much infidelity ſhould have the way to Heaven? But the inſtance in the text is full to this purpoſe; it is the very deſign of the H. Ghoſt; he proveth the general Propoſition, verſ. 16. <hi>The effectual fervent prayer of a righteous man avai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:170519:81"/>much;</hi> by a particular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, (it being <hi>in materia ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaria,</hi> prayer being a duty of univerſal neceſſity) the ſpecial example of <hi>Elijah:</hi> And it was not for his ſake that it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten onely, but for our ſakes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, the drift being <hi>a general en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement,</hi> to ſtrengthen the hands of Gods Saints <hi>in prayer</hi> againſt the ſence of their infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities: That, if <hi>Elijahs</hi> prayers were of ſuch prevalencie with God, his <hi>paſsions notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> our prayers ſhall not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn altogether fruitleſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our boſom, though we like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be incumbred with mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold corruptions; it was not ſo much the <hi>dignity of Elijah his perſon,</hi> as the integrity and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs of his heart, which rendred his prayers acceptable with God. He was an eminent Prophet indeed, but he was <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>of like paſsions with us.</hi> The <hi>infirmities</hi> of our nature, ſhall not prejudice, the <hi>fervency</hi>
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:170519:82"/>of prayers. Prayer is ſtill of as much potency with God as ever. There may be <hi>leſs of miracle</hi> in our anſwers, then there was in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lijah's;</hi> but there will be <hi>as much of love:</hi> ſurely, returns of prayer are not the fruit of our <hi>merit</hi> but of <hi>Gods free-grace;</hi> they do not depend upon the <hi>worth</hi> of the <hi>ſupplicant,</hi> but upon the <hi>merit</hi> and <hi>interceſſion</hi> of our <hi>ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Numb. 14.12.</note> And if <hi>Moſes, a ſervant</hi> prevailed by his interceſſion for an whole Nation notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their rebellions; how ſhall Chriſt <hi>the Son</hi> prevail with his Father for his dear Children notwithſtanding their infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties?
<note place="margin">Eph. 1.6.</note> 
                  <hi>He hath made us accepted in the Beloved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly,
<note place="margin">Fourth and laſt Com.</note> The time is coming (and it haſtens apace) when <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities</hi> in the Saints, whether <hi>natural</hi> or <hi>ſinful,</hi> ſhall be <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly cured:</hi> death will be an abſolute <hi>cure,</hi> death will be the <hi>death</hi> of all your <hi>corruptions.</hi> Now they do <hi>not reign,</hi> bleſſed
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:170519:82"/>be God, <hi>then</hi> they ſhall not <hi>live:</hi> now they be but ſlaves, <hi>Hewers of wood,</hi> and <hi>drawers of water;</hi> (the infirmities of the Saints find them <hi>hewing work,</hi> and <hi>weeping work;</hi>) the time is coming when they ſhall not <hi>be;</hi> the time is coming when the Saints ſhall reſt <hi>from their labours,</hi> and <hi>all tears ſhall be wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped from their eyes.</hi> Here is good news for the conflicting ſervants of God.</p>
               <p>They ſhall not alwayes pray in vain, nor ſtrive in vain, nor wreſtle in vain; God will not alwayes be wanting to their faithful endeavours; And, tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>now</hi> he is not wanting, but they are not alwayes ſo ſenſible of his preſence and aſſiſting grace with them in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts, but the time is haſtning when they ſhall weep no more, &amp; ſign no more; when they ſhall have no more cauſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain. Oh! my <hi>pride;</hi> Oh! my <hi>paſſion,</hi> and, Oh! my love
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:170519:83"/>of the world; and, Oh! my <hi>hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſy;</hi> and, Oh! my <hi>unbelief,</hi> &amp;c. But, when they ſhall ſtand upon the <hi>ſhore,</hi> and ſee all theſe <hi>Egyptians</hi> lye <hi>drowned</hi> and <hi>cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked</hi> in the <hi>red Sea</hi> of <hi>Chriſts blood;</hi> ſinging the ſong of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and of the <hi>Lumb. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto him that loved us,
<note place="margin">Rev. 15.6.</note> and waſhed us from our ſins in his own blood and hath made us</hi> KINGS <hi>and Prieſts, unto our God and his Father; to him be Glory and Dominion for ever and ever,</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>In the mean time, let the ſenſe of corruption, ſet the Saints <hi>alonging</hi> for <hi>that day;</hi> Corruption will never be totally deſtroyed till this <hi>mortal put on immortality.</hi> This curſed <hi>le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſy</hi> of ſin is ſo ſoaked &amp; pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trated into our natures, that it will never be got out till the <hi>walls of the houſe,</hi> be pulled down; <hi>Waſhing</hi> and <hi>rubbing</hi> and <hi>ſcraping</hi> will not ſerve the turn, but the whole ſtructure of nature muſt be demoliſhed:
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:170519:83"/>the body of <hi>ſin</hi> and the body of <hi>fleſt</hi> muſt be <hi>buried</hi> in one <hi>grave.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore, Let the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed of the Lord rejoice in expectation of this day;
<note place="margin">Rev. 22.20</note> let them <hi>lift up their heads with joy,
<note place="margin">Phil. 3.20.</note> becauſe their redemption draweth nigh;</hi> and having their conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation in Heaven, let them <hi>look for the Saviour,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who ſhall change</hi> THESE BODIES OF VILENESS, theſe veſſels of rottneneſs and impurity, <hi>to be like to his glorious body. Surely, I come quickly,</hi> (ſaith the Bridegroom,) let the Spirit and the Bride ſay, Come; even ſo, Come Lord Jeſus.</p>
               <p>To God onely Wiſe, be Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Glory for ever and ever, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
